Hi welcome back to part two of my extended director's cut of my GDC talk on 30 puzzle design lessons from classic puzzle communities and how those lessons can be applied to the creation of video game puzzles
大家好，欢迎回到我的GDC演讲"来自经典谜题社区的30节谜题设计课，
以及如何将这些经验应用到电子游戏谜题的创作中"的第二部分
The 11th lesson is “create a rewarding ending”
第11节课是「创造一个有收获的结局」
and the quintessential example of this is the puzzle Picross aka Nanograms
这方面最典型的例子是Picross，也就是"数织"游戏
（译者注：Nanogram数织游戏，在一个空白网格中，每行每列前面都标注有该行或该列中连续相邻黑格的长度，玩家据此来涂色）
which the Picross games have been published by Nintendo since the 90s
任天堂从90年代开始发行Picross游戏
and I think the first nanograms were published in the late 80s in various Japanese puzzle magazines.
而我认为第一个数织游戏是在80年代末发表在各种日本解谜杂志上的
There's an interesting story about the origin of them.
关于它的起源有一个有趣的故事
（译者注：由 西尾徹也 和 いしだのん 二人独立创作）
They were created by two different authors seemingly simultaneously,
数织是由两个不同作者独立创造的
but alas one of the exciting things about nanograms is at the end you sort of get this picture
数织游戏令人兴奋的一点是，在最后你会得到这样的图案
and there's always this question like what is the picture gonna be,
（在解的过程中）总会产生比如"这个图案会是什么呢？"的问题
anticipation for uh sort of that exciting moment
对那个激动人心的时刻有一种期盼
where the picture or the identity of the picture, What is it? Oh, it's a rubber duck! It's a lion! It’s finally revealed.
这个图案或图案代表的是什么呢？哦，是一只橡皮鸭！是一只狮子！最终终于被揭开了
Another example is this puzzle Spiral Galaxies which it doesn't have an ending surprise step at the end
另一个例子是"螺旋星系"谜题，它本身是没有一个惊喜的结尾的
but a variant of it does and I will show you the classic first
但它的一个变体却有，我先给你们看经典版本
So, this is the classic spiral galaxies.
这就是经典版本的螺旋星系
The goal is to partition the grid into these regions,
游戏目标是将网格划分为一些区域
each of which contains exactly one dot and the shape of the region is rotationally symmetric 180 degrees around that dot.
每个区域正好包含一个点，而且每个区域围绕那个点中心对称
It's a very interesting puzzle.
这是一个非常有趣的谜题
There's a lot of fascinating logic that goes into solving them.
深入研究的话就会有很多迷人的逻辑
But another similar type of puzzle which is printed by Nikoli under the name “Tentai Show”
不过有一种类似的谜题，是Nikoli以"Tentai show"的名字刊发的
which is a hilarious pun if you know Japanese.
如果你懂日语的话，（"Tentai Show"）这个名字还是个滑稽的双关
“taishou” means symmetry and ten means symmetry about a point
「点」(ten)是点的意思，「対称」(taishou）是对称的意思，合起来就是点对称
but “tentai” also means sort of a heavenly body like a galaxy, so, this is a show of heavenly bodies.
但「天体」(tentai)又是天体的意思，所以，这又是"天体show"
Excellent pun.
很棒的双关
Anyways digression
无论如何，有点跑题了
this was first published in Nikoli magazine in 2001 by an author who goes by Gesaku
这个在2001年首次发表在Nikoli杂志上的作品，作者叫Gesaku
and it's essentially a spiral galaxy's puzzle where some of the dots are dark colored
它本质上还是一个螺旋星系谜题，不过其中一些点是涂黑了的
and if you shade the dark colored dots, you get a shape
如果你把黑点对应的区域上色的话，就会得到一个形状
and here's a more sophisticated example quite a large instance
这里有一个更复杂的例子，相当大的一个例子
when you solve it, you get this and the shape is that of an astronaut
当你解出来的时候，你会得到一个宇航员的图形
uh quite an interesting uh composition that's been put together
非常有趣的构图
and you might ask well is the puzzle boring because of this
你可能会问，这样做了之后谜题会不会变得无聊？
does this sort of compromise the flow of the puzzle because you're having to make all of these regions fit together in exactly this way
这是否会牺牲解谜过程，因为必须得让这些区域按图形这种方式组合在一起
and the answer is mostly not
答案是大部分不会
like if you look over to the left side of this puzzle, you can kind of see there's really elaborate snaking and winding regions going all over the place
如果你看一下这个谜题的左边，你可以看到有一些精心设计的蜿蜒曲折的区域
and those are quite interesting to solve and to sort of figure out the logic of how that must be shaped
这些解起来都很有趣，而且弄清楚形状形成的逻辑也很有趣
however, putting those in sort of requires large amounts of just one color of region
然而，把这些形状融入进去就会让很多区域是同一种颜色
and that can sort of force the design
这可能会影响到设计
if you wanted to make a qr code into this then probably most of the puzzle would be relatively uninteresting to solve
如果你想弄成个二维码图案的谜题，那么谜题大部分解起来就会相对无趣了
it relies or depends heavily on uh the shape being a certain way
这在很大程度上依赖于形状本身
here's an example that kind of illustrates that
这里有一个例子可以说明这一点
this is you know I’m just putting this together to show off its GDC 2021
这个是我做的一个展现出GDC2021的图案
（译者注：用文本生成Tentai Show谜题的生成器在：https://erikdemaine.org/fonts/spiralgalaxies/）
but this is actually made using a text generator by Erik Demaine and Martin Demaine
我这个实际上是用Erik Demaine和Martin Demaine的文本生成器来生成的
and it shows you know you can do whatever you want with these Tentai Show puzzles
这个就表面了你可以用任何图案来制作Tentai Show谜题
but like you know this is the 2 and it's just a diagonal set of one by one things
但你看这是个2，它只是一个一个点斜着摆放而已
it's not particularly interesting or solve or fun to solve
这个解起来并不是特别有趣
another example of putting a surprise at the end of the puzzle
另一个在谜题结尾加入惊喜的例子是
are the extraction steps that occur in puzzle hunts like the MIT mystery hunt
在解谜寻宝比赛中的"提炼步骤"，比如MIT解谜寻宝比赛
（译者注：元谜题 meta puzzle，几个谜题的答案本身又组成一个新的谜题）
where every single puzzle has a solution that is a word or a phrase and often those are used in metapuzzles or other things
在那里面每道谜题的答案都是一个单词或短语，而这些答案又常被用于"元谜题"之类的东西
here's a Tentai show puzzle whose answer is actually a five letter word
这里有一道Tentai Show谜题，它的答案是一个五个字母的单词
and if you solve it, you get this and maybe you can guess what the five letter word answer is
如果你解开它，你会得到这样一个图案，那么你也许能猜出这个答案是什么
of course, it is clubs
当然，答案是"梅花♣"
（译者注：pavelspuzzles.com/aenigmas/）
this is by Pavel Curtis from his blog Adalogical Ænigmas
这个谜题是来自Pavel Curtis的博客Adalogical Ænigmas
which has a lot of interesting puzzles that have a word or phrase as an answer
他有很多用一个单词或短语作为答案的有趣的谜题
the extraction steps have a couple of values
"提炼步骤"有几个方面的价值
they provide this additional final eureka moment which can be especially exciting if you're anticipating it or there's a little bit of a surprise at the end
它们提供了最后这样一个额外的尤里卡时刻，如果你期待它出现的话，那么它会非常令人兴奋
they also exploit the peak end rule which means uh well the the things that people tend to remember the most are are sort of the the peak or the most salient part of an experience as well as the ending or the last thing
它们还利用了「峰终定律(Peak-End Rule)」：
人们倾向于记住一段体验中的高峰或最突出的部分，以及结尾部分
and so, if the last part of an experience is somehow exciting or memorable
因此，如果一个体验的结尾部分是令人激动或难忘的话，
then overall the experience will be viewed more positively
那么总体来说，这个体验会被更加积极地看待
and so that's true of puzzles like these
而谜题也是如此
it also can create setups for metapuzzles where words like clubs can be used as ingredients in another puzzle
它还能为元谜题创造条件，像"梅花"这样的单词可以被用作另一个谜题的成分
and many uh puzzle hunts like MIT mystery hunter
而许多解谜寻宝比赛，比如MIT解谜寻宝比赛，
set up with these meta puzzles that are sort of like boss puzzles
会设置这样的元谜题来作为类似说最后的Boss谜题
where there might be 12 other puzzles you need to solve and then you take those 12 words and you use them to solve this final puzzle
你可能得先解决另外12个谜题，然后拿着这12个单词来解决这最后的谜题
and maybe only eight to ten of those twelve are actually needed
或者也许实际上只需要其中8到10个单词
so, uh it can create a sort of progression gate where you don't necessarily need to solve everything but you need to solve most of it
所以这样可以创造一种阶段性门槛，你不一定得解决全部谜题，可能解决其中大部分就行了
um and that can be very useful for uh pacing and structuring a puzzle hunt
这对于设置解谜寻宝比赛的节奏和步骤非常有用
lesson number 12 is to embed secrets and surprises
第12课是「藏入一些秘密和惊喜」
and this is sort of another way of cramming more eureka moments into the same puzzle
这算是向同一道谜题中塞入更多尤里卡时刻的另一种方式
（译者注：Cryptic Crossword是一种在英国特别流行的填字游戏，其中每个词的线索都是一个字谜）
I’ll show you one example from cryptic crosswords
我给你看一个Cryptic Crossword的例子
these things are called Ninas and they are sort of little easter eggs hidden in a puzzle
这种东西被称作「Nina」，它们算是藏在谜题中的小彩蛋
in this puzzle if you read the words going around the outside or the letters it will say
在这道谜题中，如果你把沿着外框周围的字母按顺序读出来就是：
"Monty Python’s Flying Circus" , sort of going sequentially around the border of the puzzle
"Monty Python's Flying Circus"（《巨蟒剧团之飞翔的马戏团》）
and this is known as a Nina
这就是所谓的 "Nina"
the name Nina comes from Al Hirschfeld who's a uh he was a comic author in the US
"Nina"这个叫法来自Al Hirschfeld，他是美国的一位漫画家
and Nina is the name of his daughter
Nina是他女儿的名字
and here you can see the word Nina is actually hidden in the hair of this character three separate times
在这里你可以看到"Nina"这个词实际上是藏在这个人物的头发里的，有三个地方
you can see the N-I-N-A
你可以看到N-I-N-A的字母
and he signs his name with a little 3 next to it indicating that there are three Ninas hidden in this one particular comic
他在署名的时候在旁边加了个小的数字3，表面这个漫画中藏了3个"Nina"
and he did this throughout his career after his daughter was born
在他整个职业生涯中，自从他女儿出生之后他都是如此做的
and so Ninas are essentially the untracked secrets or easter eggs of UK crosswords
所以"Nina"本质上是英国填字游戏中隐藏着的秘密或者说彩蛋
and one feature of them that's very notable is that they are missable
它们的一个显著特点是，它们是"可错过的"
you could go through this entire crossword solve the whole thing think you were done and not even realize there was something there
你可能把整个填字游戏解出来了，觉得自己做完了，甚至都没有意识到那你还有什么东西
uh is this a problem or is it a feature
那这算是个缺点还是特性呢？
uh well I mean one issue with it being missable is sort of that eureka moment is just not going to be experienced by the whole audience of this puzzle
这种"可错过的"东西所带来的一个问题是，它对应的尤里卡时刻是没法被所有玩家都体验到的
but on the other hand, the fact that the secret is missable somehow makes it more valuable
但另一方面，这个秘密是"可错过的"这一点，在某种程度上又使它本身更有价值
it creates uh this feeling whenever you're solving one of these this author's puzzles let's say that there might just always be something lurking around the corner
它创造了这样一种感觉，每当你在做这个作者的谜题时，总会觉得在角落里会藏着什么东西
and when you do find it it's more of a surprise
而当你找到它的时候就会有更多的惊喜
and as we learned earlier that the sort of more surprising or unexpected something is the more exciting it is the more dopaminergic it is the the more sparkle is there
而正如前面学到的，越是令人惊讶或意外的东西，
就越令人兴奋、有越高多巴胺能、有更多Sparkle
so, the fact that the secrets are missable provides uh sort of additional excitement when you do find it
所以，秘密是可错过的这一点会让你在解开它的时候有额外的兴奋
um another thing that missable secrets can do especially in video games is they can provide a reason to sort of go back to an old game
可错过的秘密能做到的另一件事是，特别是在电子游戏中，它能提供一个回去玩老游戏的原因
uh like if I go back to a game like Chrono Trigger which is an RPG from the 90s
比如我回去玩《超时空之轮》这样的90年代的RPG
uh there are things you can discover in that game that you didn't discover when you played it the first time
你会发现一些你第一次玩的时候没发现的东西
whether it's a line of dialogue or it's a sort of a hidden item that you just never knew was there
不论是一段对话或者某个隐藏物品，你之前不知道它的存在
there are so many things and so much depth in a good rpg that you can play it multiple times
一个好的RPG里面有很多东西、很多深度，你可以反反复复玩
and I think some puzzle games like the Witness are starting to incorporate more and more of this into their games as well which is great
我觉得一些解谜游戏，如《见证者》，也开始在里面融入更多这样的东西，这一点很不错
um lesson number 13 aporia is a promise of surprise
第13课「Aporia(困惑)是惊喜的前兆」
aporia is a state when you're solving a puzzle where you as a solver believe that the puzzle is impossible
Aporia（困惑）是解谜时的一种状态，作为解谜者，你感觉这个谜题是不可能的
you may even feel like you have a proof that it's impossible
甚至感觉自己能找到证据证明它是不可能的
I need to do this… but there's a catch! I just can't
“我需要这样做...但有个难点！我做不到”
what's the trick?
“这里面有什么诀窍？”
um this may also be called a “known unknown”
这也可以被称作“已知的未知”
where you as a solver know that there is something that you don't know
作为一个解谜者，你知道有一些你不知道的东西
you think that ah well I mean this this puzzle is in this game or this person has you know built and shipped this puzzle to me which I have in my hands it must have a solution
你会觉得既然这个谜题已经摆在我面前了，那总能解得出来吧
and yet I convinced myself that I believe it has no solution
但我总还是相信这东西解不出来
uh an example a simple example is with this puzzle here uh that I created uh
举一个简单的例子，这是我制作的一个谜题。
I’ll show you how it works
我给你看看它怎么玩的
uh let's switch to the full cam um
让我切下摄像头
this object right here we'll call the cage
这个东西，我把它叫做“笼子”
and there are two other parts which I will call A and B
还有另外两个部分，我称之为A和B
here's A it's sort of got the L-shaped Tetris piece connected to the S-shape
这是A，它有点像L型的俄罗斯方块跟S型的连在一起
and this is B. B sort of has this three-way junction up near the top
这是B，B的顶部有个像三通一样形状
and the goal is to sort of put A and B into the cage
目标是把A和B插入“笼子”
and well let's just slide A in you can kind of put it in like that
让我们把A放进去，你可以像这样把它放进去
and that's the only place it goes it's very easy to see that
这是它唯一能放的地方，很容易看出来
and then you try and put b in
然后你试着把B放进去
and it just like it won't fit. there's not enough room to slide it in
然后它就放不进去了，没有足够的空间
uh you could try putting it in from the bottom it
你可以试着从底部把它放进去
there's no room to put it in there either
那里也没有空间可以放进去
okay well maybe you don't put A in first. Maybe you have to put B in first
好吧，可能不能先把A放进去，也许得先把B放进去
and uh you can try that
你可以试着这样做
you know here's b in I’ll just slide it down there
这个是B，我把它放到这个位置
uh but then you have to put A and you	 can kind of see where it goes
但然后你放A进去，你可以看它的位置
right like it's kind of kind of wrap around there and slide in there but you just you can't slide it in
它有点像把它包裹住了，放不进去
there's no way to make it work
这样也不行
so, it's not A before B and it's not B before A
所以，既不是先放A再放B，也不是先放B再放A
well then it must be impossible, right
那么这一定是不可能的，对吗？
but no actually the solution is you take B and you put it in kind of halfway and you stick it up there
但不是的，实际上解法是你把B放到一半，然后就先不动它
and then you can kind of just put A in half way and slide it in the back
然后又把A放入到一半的位置，然后从后面把它塞进去
and then b comes down
然后B就下来了
and there we go and then it's solved uh
就这样就解决了
so, you know the trick is you have to put A in halfway
所以，诀窍是你必须把A放在一半的地方
um back to the presentation
回到幻灯片
uh so I mean and this isn't a difficult puzzle
所以我的意思是，这其实并不是一个很难的谜题
this might be a level one or a level two puzzle it's not particularly challenging
这可能是第1级或第2级的谜题，没有特别的挑战性
but it illustrates the point of the obvious things lead to a non-solution to the puzzle
但它说明了一点，解谜过程中会有一些明显的东西让这个谜题看起来无解
and you might even be convinced like well then this puzzle's impossible
并且你甚至可能会说服自己这个谜题是不可能的
you can't put a in first you can't put b in first so clearly it's impossible well okay
既不能先放A也不能先放B那显然就不可能了
but there was something that you didn't notice
但其实有些事情你没有注意到
the state of aporia this state of feeling like the puzzle is impossible
这种Aporia的感觉，这种觉得谜题不可能的感觉
or simultaneously believing both that well I think it's impossible but yet the puzzle is in front of me and a solution has been promised
或者说既感觉这个谜题是不可能，但又觉得这个谜题的解一定是能给出的
um it creates this uh idea that an interesting trick exists
这产生了这样一个想法，一个有趣的诀窍是存在的
it sort of promises you that a powerful eureka moment is coming and primes you for the discovery of something really cool
它有点在向你预示一个强大的尤里卡时刻即将到来，并让你为发现很酷的东西做准备
and that mystery and anticipation is really motivating like there's a big reveal coming and you can now anticipate it
那种神秘感和期待真的很有激励性，就像有个大的启示即将到来，已经可以预见它了
and the sort of state of anticipating a reward or anticipating a eureka moment is it can be more motivating and more dopaminergic than actually getting the reward
那种期待奖励或尤里卡时刻的状态，比实际得到奖励更有动力，有更高多巴胺能
um and so this state of aporia is highly motivating
所以这种Aporia的状态时有高度激励性的
and when a player is convinced that they're just on the cusp of a really cool discovery
而当玩家相信自己正处在即将有一个非常酷的发现的边缘的时候
that could be a time where they're very unlikely to quit and very likely to remember
这就是他们不太可能放弃的时刻，而且很可能会记住（这个时刻）
and uh you know want to share that discovery once they found it and be very excited by it
而一旦他们解出来了，就会想与别分享，并为之兴奋
so aporia is a great trick
所以Aporia是一个很好的技巧
I will show you an example this is from a game called Pipe Push Paradise by Corey Martin a few years back
我给你看个例子，这是几年前由Corey Martin制作的叫《推管天堂》的游戏
this is a puzzle where you sort of have to push these pipes around
谜题中你得把这些管道推来推去
and in this puzzle in particular on the left here you have this pipe with water flowing out
在这个谜题的左边你能看到一个在流水的管道
and you have to connect it to the one on the right
你得把它跟右边那个连起来
and you might realize well okay so you just have to make this u shape with these two pieces
你可能会意识到，好吧，只需要用这两段管道做成这样一个U字形
you can sort of flip and rotate the pieces around
你可以翻转和旋转这些管道段
the problem is that when you get to this state you can't leave the puzzle
问题是，当你做成这个状态时，你就不能走出这个谜题了
and you have to both connect the pipes up and have a way of exiting
你必须把管道连接起来并且还要有一个出口
in this case the exit is at the bottom but you just can't get down there
在这种情况下，出口在底部，但你走不过去
and uh you know once you've played with this puzzle a bit you can realize that
一旦你玩过这个谜题，你就会发现
there's no way to be at the puzzle at the bottom of this puzzle while also having the pipes in this configuration
没有办法把管道弄成这种构造的同时人站在下面
there's just no last move that could have created this configuration and leave you at the bottom
没有任何移动能做出这样的构造，而让你站在底部
you could never have pushed those pipes up into that configuration because there wouldn't have been a place for you to stand um
你不可能把这些管道推到这个位置，因为你根本没有地方可以站立
and one of the things that you'll observe if you're playing around with this puzzle enough is that
如果你多玩一玩，你就会发现
you can actually rotate the pipes into a different configuration where they're out in three dimensions
你可以把管道旋转到另一种构造，让它们在三维空间中突出来
this is a three-dimensional puzzle solving game where the rotations sometimes take things up off of the floor
这其实是个三维的解谜游戏，旋转是可以让东西离开地面的
and this prompts you to find the real solution which is actually to make the archway in the third dimension
这就促使你找到真正的解法，就是把“拱门”变成三维的
such that you can walk under it and leave the puzzle
这样你就可以从下面走过去，离开这个谜题
and this is a very memorable solution
这是一个非常令人难忘的解法
but the thing that sort of primes you for this surprise is going back to your first attempt at the solution and realizing this ain't gonna work
但在这个惊喜之前，回到你最初的尝试，你会发现做不到
and perhaps even being so puzzled by it that you might leave the puzzle go try something else
也许你会感到非常困惑，以至于暂时离开这个谜题去试试别的
and then come back once you've realized that well all the other puzzles had solutions
然后当你意识到其他的谜题都有解决方法时又回来
this one must have one but what am i not thinking of
那这个谜题也一定可解，但是我有什么地方是没想到的吗
and that final surprise is just so memorable
而最后的惊喜是如此令人难忘
both because it's an exciting surprise but also because of the fact that you couldn't solve it any other means
既是因为它是一个令人兴奋的惊喜，但也是因为你无法用其他任何方式来解决它的这一点事实
now in order to make this work you have to do this which is our 14th lesson
那么，为了让它发挥作用，你必须要做的事正是我们接下来的第14课
cultivate the trust of the solver
「建立与解谜者之间的信任」
and one example of where this comes up is say you're on the puzzle subreddit or the puzzling stack exchange and you just click on a random interesting puzzle
有一个例子可以说明这一点，比如你跑到贴吧上或其他网站上随便找了个看起很有趣的谜题
and it looks cool but you play around with it a bit and it looks impossible
它看起来很酷，但你尝试了一会儿，发现这个看起来解不出来
and maybe you've even convinced yourself that it must be impossible you have a proof that it's impossible
也许你甚至说服了自己这肯定不可能，你有证据说明它不可能
maybe there's a really cool eureka moment lurking beneath the surface that you just didn't discover yet
也许有一个非常酷的尤里卡时刻埋藏在表面之下，只是你还没有发现
but on the other hand maybe just there's a rule missing, there's a piece missing
但另一方面，也许可能只是缺了条规则，谜题少了一块
maybe the person who made this puzzle screwed up or maybe the puzzle uh the poster of the puzzle screwed up
也许制作这道谜题的人搞错了，或者是发帖的人搞错了
and just forgot to include something
而忘了把一些东西加进去
maybe it's intended to be impossible,
也许这道谜题就是故意无解的
maybe it's you know one of these famous Konigsberg bridge style puzzles that literally has no solution and discovering why is sort of the interesting part of it
也许这就是类似柯尼斯堡七桥问题那种无解的谜题，而去发现为什么无解是它的有趣之处
and I’ve literally seen all of the above on these websites
在这些网站上，我见过上述所有情况
but if it's from a source that I trust or it has a lot of upvotes then maybe it's worth pursuing anyway you know
但如果谜题是来自我信任的地方，或者有很多人点赞的话，也许就值得一试了
but uh the ability for me to trust that this puzzle is actually something interesting is often limited
但如果只是一个我不认识的人随便在哪个网站随便发的个帖子的话，
if it's just you know a random post on a random website from somebody I don't know
那么我去相信这个谜题是真正有趣的可能就很有限了
and I might give up on it before I actually push forward and find that interesting eureka moment
我可能会在我真正找到那个有趣的尤里卡时刻之前就放弃它了
this happens a lot in video games, especially action adventure games in Metroidvania
这种事情在电子游戏中经常发生，特别是在类银河恶魔城和动作冒险游戏中
let's say you see an interesting puzzle you know there's this heart piece being teased over here in the corner in Zelda
就比如说在塞尔达里面，你看到这样一个谜题，在角落里有一颗心可以去拿
Can I get it right now?
我现在能拿得到吗？
Maybe I’m missing an item. Maybe I have to come back once I find the hook shot or the glider or whatever
或许我缺一样物品，可能得等我有勾爪或滑翔伞之后再回来拿
maybe there's an ability I don't have
或许有一种技能是我没有的
maybe the world itself will change. Maybe you know in act three they'll be moving platforms and mushroom sprouting here that I could jump on
或许世界本身会改变，也许可能到第三幕中，这里会出现移动平台或者蘑菇，我可以跳上去
maybe when I become adult link instead of child link I’ll be able to jump that far
或许等我成为成年林克时就能跳这么远了
maybe the game has a bug
或许游戏有bug
This has happened to me so many times where I play an indie puzzle game the first week it comes out and it just hasn't had a patch yet
我在玩那种刚发售一周还没修复的独立游戏时，遇到过太多这种情况了
and there's some kind of issue with one of the puzzles where I you know I just can't solve it
里面的谜题会出现各种问题，怎么也解决不了
and the problem with that is once that happens to you once, you no longer have any trust in the rest of the game
问题是，一旦你遇到这种情况，只需要一次，你就会对游戏剩下部分失去信任了
like every time you get stuck on a puzzle you might just think well what if the game's bugged again, right
比如每当你卡在一个谜题的时候，就会想，会不会是游戏又出bug了，是吧？
uh it puts you in a state where you're no longer sort of following that drip feed of
这让你处于一种状态，你不再像以前那样觉得在跟随着游戏的进程
like oh i'm just on the cusp of something exciting I just need to push forward a little bit
处在激动人心时刻的边缘，只要再往前推进一下就好了
instead there's this sort of unhealthy skepticism that robs you of that motivating force to continue going in
取而代之的是一种不健康的怀疑态度，使你失去了继续前进的动力
this case for this Zelda puzzle it turns out you can get it at this stage of the game
就这个塞尔达谜题而言，在游戏的这个阶段，你是可以拿得到的
you just have to go grab a chicken and you have to carry the chicken up quite a ways
你只需要去抓一只鸡，然后带着这只鸡走一段路
but then you can sort of use it to sail over there because when you're holding the chicken you fall much less slowly
然后你就可以拿着鸡飘过去，因为拿着鸡的时候，下落速度会慢很多
and so it in fact does have a solution but that may not be obvious to you until much later in the game
所以它实际上是有解决方案的，但你可能要到游戏的很后期才会发现
uh a way of dealing with this that Supraland used
《Supraland》里面用了一种方法来解决这个问题
was to actually have NPCs that tell you have everything you need to solve this puzzle, go for it uh
是让NPC告诉你，“你已经有解决这个谜题所需的一切东西，去解吧”
and this happens at multiple times in the game
而这种方式在游戏中多次出现
in some cases you'll even reach an area where you can no longer go back
在某些情况下，你甚至会到达一个你回不去的地方
like you have to fall off something and it locks you in a room
比如你得从某个地方跳下去，然后把你锁在一个房间中
with an npc says you says you could solve this puzzle right now and then you just have to do it
有个NPC告诉你现在就可以解决这个难题，然后你就必须去做
and Supraland is a Metroidvania where you're constantly getting new items that add new abilities or affordances to the player
《Supraland》是一个类银河恶魔城游戏，你会不断得到新物品，为玩家增加新能力
and so, you might often come to a puzzle that you can't solve and say well maybe I just have to come back once I get an item
所以，你可能经常碰到无法解决的谜题，然后说，也许我得拿到一个物品后再回来
and so, if that were the case for every puzzle in the game
因此，如果游戏中每个谜题都出现这种情况的话
then the for the puzzles that gate your progression you know the player might just turn around and go do something else
那对于那些推进游戏进程的谜题来说，玩家可能就转身去做别的事去了
and so, something like this is in fact necessary
所以，像这样的东西其实是有必要的
to sort of tell the player no you need to push forward on this one puzzle
它可以告诉玩家，不，你需要在这个谜题上继续努力
even though it's hard you can do it um
尽管谜题有些难，但你可以做到
and Supraland was a very highly reviewed game it was 96 positive on steam
《Supraland》是一款评价很高的游戏，在steam上有96%的好评
it was one of my favorite puzzle games of this whole year
它也是我那一整年最喜欢的解谜游戏之一
um but you know many people might think this is breaking the fourth wall
但很多人可能认为这是在打破第四面墙
it's a little bit distasteful there's some kind of dissonance going on here between the character and the player and what's happening and
这有点让人反感，在角色和玩家之间产生了不协调
David Münnich is a very experienced puzzle creator
David Münnich（《Supraland》的作者）是一位非常有经验的谜题创作者
he was the creator of the original Notpron which was the most famous internet riddle of sort of the flash internet era back in the early to mid-2000s
他是《Notpron》最初的制作者，这是00年代前中期Flash游戏时代最出名的解谜游戏
and so, he's been creating puzzles for a long time and understands very well the experience that a solver goes through when they're solving a puzzle
所以，他已经创作了很长时间的谜题，并且非常了解解谜者在解谜时的体验
and he felt it was necessary to do this because he wanted to preserve the sanctity of the player's trust that the puzzle itself is solvable
他觉得有必要这样做，因为他想保持玩家对谜题本身可解的信任的同时
while also making a Metroidvania where you're getting new items all the time that do new things
制作出一个类银河恶魔城游戏，在其中玩家会不断得到新物品、做新的事情
so, an interesting solution to the problem
所以，这是个有趣解决方案
a related idea is that of “square dealing”
一个相关的观点是“公平交易”(Square Dealing)
which uh it's a term that I’ve seen in crossword communities and other puzzle communities
这是我在填字游戏社区和其他解谜社区看到的一个术语
but it basically refers to the conventions that the constructors of puzzles are abiding by to play fair um
它本质上是指的是谜题创作者为了让玩家顺利玩下去而遵守的惯例
and you'll see many of these conventions
你会看到有很多这样的惯例
for example in puzzle hunts they will never have anagrams without a clue
你如在解谜寻宝中，他们不会出没给线索的同字母异构词
and the reason is because when you're doing a puzzle hunt puzzle these are typically puzzles where the rules are not provided
原因是当你在做解谜寻宝时，这些谜题通常没有提供规则
and you have to figure out what it is that you need to do
你需要做的就是找出这些（规则）是什么
you might literally try anagraming everything
你可能会试着把所有词的异构词都尝试一遍
you could dump every word in this puzzle the title of every puzzle whatever into anagram generators
你可能会把谜题中的每个词、每个谜题的标题都放到异构词生成器中
and just come up with nothing or come up with something that's maybe tenuously there but turns out to be nothing
然后什么都没有得到
and that experience as a solver is not a pleasant experience
作为一个解题者，这种体验并不愉快
so, to you know save the solver from having to do that
所以，为了让解谜者不去做这种事情
the uh the authors of puzzle hunt puzzles will just tell you right up front there are no unclued anagrams in this puzzle hunt
解谜寻宝的作者会直接告诉你，这里面没有那种没提供线索的同字母异构词
and that will be part of the rules that are communicated to the player um
而这也是传达给玩家的规则的一部分
Cryptic Crosswords have a similar convention where they don't do indirect anagrams
Cryptic Crossword也有类似的惯例，它们不会有不直接的异构词
which is basically like uh you know if there's an anagram it has to be clued by a trigger word
基本上就是说，如果里面有一个异构词，那么它就必须由一个触发词来提示
and it can't be mixed with another type of hint
而且不能和其他类型的线索混在一起
escape rooms have some conventions like “one key one lock “
密室逃脱也有一些惯例，比如“一个钥匙对应一把锁”
if you get a four-digit code, you're never gonna have to put it in multiple different four-digit combination locks
如果你得到了一个四位的密码，那你永远也不需要在多个密码锁上输入它
because again that would just be irritating
因为那也会让人很不爽
are you do you want the player to have to retry everything over and over again no
你想让玩家一次又一次地重试之前所有的东西吗？
so, one key one lock is sort of a convention that saves the sanity of some players
所以，“一个钥匙对应一把锁”是一种惯例，可以拯救玩家的San值
now whether or not this is advertised or told to the players before they begin
至于是否在宣传的时候或者在玩之间就告诉玩家
it's you know it's kind of 50-50. it depends on which escape room you're doing
可能五五开吧，这取决于你玩的哪家密室逃脱
uh no outside knowledge is another common convention
不依赖外界信息也是另一个常见的惯例
but it's sort of like if you're a solver of Cryptics
然而，如果你是一个比如说Cryptic Crossword的老手，
you probably realize this no indirect anagrams rule
你可能会意识到无不直接的异构词这个规则
even if it's just subconsciously because you just never see it right
即便这只是潜意识的，因为你从来没有见过它出现
you just realize that oh well they wouldn't print that I don't have to do that
你只是意识到，他们不会出这种谜题，我不需要这么做
but beginners may not understand this and may never even really have learned it unless somebody taught them
但新手可能不明白这一点，除非有人教他们否则他们没办法知道
so, beginners can spend a lot of time on cryptics just trying stuff that is never possibly necessary
所以新手可能会花很多时间在谜题上去尝试一些根本没必要的事情
because they don't understand the conventions of the genre right
因为他们不了解这类谜题的惯例
so square dealing is important
所以Square Dealing很重要
But in video games especially it's also important to communicate those rules to the player
但在电子游戏中，向玩家传达这些规则也很重要
because every puzzle game you play will have different rules about how the puzzles are designed and what's allowed and what's not
因为每个解谜游戏关于怎么设计的、什么能做什么不能做的规则都是不同的
and sometimes it's not that explicit
而且有时并不那么明确
some games actually tell the player
而有些游戏实际上会直接告诉玩家
and this is a game called Ittle Dew which is sort of a Zelda-like
这是一个叫《Ittle Dew》的游戏，是一个类塞尔达的游戏
and after you exit the first dungeon it literally tells you there's no missable items or chests in dungeons at all
在你离开第一个地牢后，它会直接告诉你，已经没有可错过的物品或箱子了
and not every Zelda-like has these types of conventions
而并非每个类塞尔达游戏都有这种惯例
and in classic Zelda’s usually the convention is there's no need to return to dungeons later
而在经典塞尔达中，通常的惯例是之后就不用回到之前的地牢了
meaning that every item that you could get in a dungeon is one that you could get with sort of the key or progression items from that dungeon and earlier or and the prerequisites
意味着在地牢里得到的每件物品都是可以通过钥匙或者进展物品而得到的
although that's not true in every Zelda and it's not true in uh every dungeon of every Zelda
虽然不是每一部塞尔达都是如此，而不是每个地牢都是如此
so, um having that type of square dealing is useful
所以，有这种类似“Square Dealing”的原则是有用的
and communicating it to the player can really help build that trusting relationship that allows the player to sort of press on when they're stuck on a puzzle
将其传达给玩家可以帮助建立信任关系，让玩家在被卡住的时候可以继续前进
the sort of contrapositive to that is avoid cheap tricks
而与之对应的则是“避免使用拙劣的把戏”
I’m going to pick on the Talos principle
我要批评一下《塔罗斯法则》
when it released it had a puzzle where
当它刚发布的时候，有这样一个谜题
well this isn't one of the main puzzles in the game, it's actually one of the bonus puzzles that you have to get stars for
这不是游戏里的主线谜题，是要拿星星的支线谜题
but one of the stars and it's very early on in the game
但其中有一颗星星很早就在游戏里出现了
it's in the first uh first major area of the fourth world of that
就在第四个世界的第一个主要区域里
uh there is a hidden reflector up in a tree that you have to aim a laser at
有一个隐藏在树上的反射器，你必须用激光瞄准它
and uh up until this point in the game all the reflectors are just items on the ground you can pick them up and move them
而在游戏的这个阶段，所有反射器都是在地上的，你可拿起并移动它们
this one is stationary and it's in a tree
而这一个是固定的，而且在树上
and in no other part of the game do you ever have to look up in the tree for anything
在游戏的其他部分，你都不需要在树上找东西
and there are so many other things that you can try to solve this puzzle that almost barely work
还有很多其他东西可以尝试来解决这个谜题，但都没用
I literally wasted I don't know more than an hour trying to get this thing and then to learn that the answer was well it was in a tree
我真的浪费了可能一个多小时来解这个，然后得知答案是它在一棵树上
uh that was kind of upsetting
这让人很不爽
but also, it made me distrust the developer
但同时，这也让我不再相信开发者了
because for every other puzzle in that game instead of pressing on when I was stuck,
因为对那个游戏中其他谜题，当我卡住了我不会再不停尝试
I just had this thought well what if it's some more *** like that reflector in the tree
取而代之的是这样的想法：“这个会不会又是像树上的反光镜那样的***呢？”
um it turns out that after the game launched they actually patched it
不过游戏发售之后，他们把这个改了
and they changed that reflector in the tree to a reflector on a very prominent salient pillar that you could see from all directions
他们把树上的反射器改成了放在一个非常显眼的柱子上，从各个方向都看得到
uh that made it clear that there was a reflector up there
这样一来就很清楚上面有一个反射器
and then it became a mystery of what's that reflector on the pillar for, turns out one of the secret bonus stars
然后就成了一个谜题：那根柱子上的反射器是干什么的？原来是为了一颗星星
and this is sort of a much more honest way of designing this puzzle
这种设计谜题的方式就更加诚实得多
and it prevents that player's mind from being poisoned by well am I going to have to look in a tree forever
这样可以避免玩家的思维被“我需不需要接下来都在树上找东西”的想法所毒害
I’m going to uh quote my good friend weihuawho said
我想引用我的好朋友黄炜华的一句话
“a good puzzle has an ‘aha’ moment a bad puzzle has an ‘oh really’ moment”
“一个好谜题有‘啊哈’(Aha)时刻，一个坏谜题有‘啊？真的吗？’(Oh really?)时刻”
um wei-hua has a four-time world puzzle champion and he's been published uh everywhere
黄炜华是世界谜题锦标赛的四届冠军，到处都有他发表的作品
he's done crosswords for new york times he's done world puzzle championship stuff
他为《纽约时报》做过填字游戏，为世界谜题锦标赛做过东西
he's a game designer as well and done physical puzzles uh
他也是一个游戏设计师，也做过实物解谜
this guy is one of the most experienced puzzle creators I know
他是我认识的最有经验的谜题创作者之一
and for him you know this oh really moment this discovery of like it was that all along is uh a very negative experience when you're expecting or hoping
对他来说，这种"啊？真的吗？"时刻就是那种你一直期待或坚持之后却得到了一个消极的体验
instead for an exciting eureka um
而不是一个令人激动的尤里卡时刻
Bob Bates refers to that as poisoning of the well
Bob Bates将此称为 "向井里投毒"
bob bates designed a lot of uh adventure games point-and-click games for Infocom and legend entertainment in the late 80s and 90s
Bob Bates在80、90年代末为Infocom和Legend entertainment
设计了大量冒险游戏和点击游戏
and bob actually gave a gdc talk where he sort of emphasized that a good understanding of puzzle design theory was necessary to
实际上Bob在GDC的演讲中强调了对谜题设计理论的良好理解是必要的
avoid this pitfall of creating a state in players where there's sort of this unhealthy skepticism that the designers aren't playing fair
以避免落入这样的陷阱，让玩家产生认为设计者不公正的一种不健康的怀疑态度
uh and here you know here's just a general list of things to avoid
这里是一个你要避免的一个清单
um anything that requires you to do lots of searching without a clue
任何让玩家在没有提示的情况下去做大量搜索行为的东西
darkness is a big one if there are dark corners of your game and literally the player has to walk into every one of them
黑暗会是个大问题，如果游戏有黑暗的角落而玩家得一一尝试走进去的话
or even walk into every one of them and jump in order to find that hidden nook where you might have hidden something
或者甚至为了找到可能藏有东西的隐蔽角落而在每个黑暗角落都跳一下
that's that can be irritating
这就会让人很不爽
wall pressing if the player has to touch every wall, shoot every wall, press the action box on every wall um
“Wall Pressing”指如果玩家必须摸下每一面墙，射击每一面墙，对每面墙都按下操作键...
if there are invisible platforms the player can't see them and they just have to jump randomly to see where there might be an invisible platform
如果有玩家看不见的隐藏平台，玩家就只能随机地跳来找哪里有隐藏平台
those types of experiences can be very draining for players
如果玩家想完成你的谜题的话，这种体验是非常耗费精力的
because uh instead of feeling like they're on the right track
因为玩家并不觉得自己走在正确的道路上
they're feeling like they're just sort of laboriously searching the entire possible game for the thing you might have hidden if they want to sort of complete the puzzles
而只是觉得在费力地在整个游戏中寻找你可能藏起来的东西
so, you never want to do this
所以，你永远不会想这样做
and the other thing that can happen is like say you had a clue which illustrated oh well you're going to have to jump in the dark
还有一种情况是，比如说你给了个提示，告诉玩家得在黑暗中跳跃
maybe the player didn't see that clue and they just happened to wander that way and find it
或许玩家并没有看到那个提示，只是碰巧走到这个找到了这个谜题
the problem is if the player comes out and realized well there was no clue I guess I have to check every dark zone anywhere um
问题是，如果没有发现这个提示，那我想我又得去每个黑暗区域一个一个看了
that is sort of an equal well poisoning right
这就跟之前说的“向井里投毒”没区别了
so, you not just have to make sure you put the clue
所以，你不仅要确保你给了提示
you have to make sure that the player can't get there without the clue
你还得确保玩家在不知道提示的情况下就无法到达那里
you have to make sure the clue is somehow sort of obvious
你必须确保提示在某种程度上是明显的
or at least the you know maybe when the players coming back out they will then see the clue
或者至少，当玩家往回走，他们能看到这个提示
you know a way to avoid that
你知道有方法是可以避免这种情况的
you don't want to have puzzles that suddenly increase tenuousness
不要让谜题突然变得不确定起来
like force the player to do something they never had to do
比如让玩家做一些他们之前从来不需要做的事情
force the player to look outside the game when they never had to look outside the game
比如突然让玩家在游戏外去寻找，而他们从未这么做过
uh you know some kind of new trick or method that is suddenly used or required
突然要求玩家使用一种新的技巧或方法
especially if it's a one-off if you only have to use it once
尤其是如果这种方法是一次性的、只需要用一次的话
well will the player now be paranoid that they have to use it again
那么，玩家现在会不会就偏执地认为他们之后必须再次使用它呢？
will they try it on every other puzzle in the rest of the game
他们会不会在接下来的每个谜题中都尝试这个方法呢？
you want to make sure that you don't have that situation
你要确保不会出现这种情况
inconsistency in general if the rules are changing
如果规则一直变化的话，一般会产生不一致
then players will never know whether they can expect their understanding of the game, their conceptual model for how the game systems work to be correct if they're questioning the conceptual model
如果玩家不断地质疑游戏的概念模型的话，玩家将永远无法确定他们能否理解这个游戏，
无法确定他们理解的游戏系统的概念模型是否正确
then they're not in a good space to do problem solving right
那么他们就没有处在解决问题的良好的状态，对吧？
you want players to feel that they rock solid understand the game's rules the game's logic and are then solving things
你想让玩家对游戏的规则逻辑有坚实的理解，然后再解决谜题
rather than questioning that
而不是去质疑它
at least if you're making a game that's about logic or about understanding rules
至少对于如果你制作的游戏是关于逻辑或关于理解规则的话
there are some games that are just not about that and that's okay
有些游戏不是关于这个的，那这也没什么
there are some games that are just about rule discovery
有一些游戏只是关于规则的发现
but that brings us to point number 15 which is “be careful with intransparencies”
这就让我们来到了第15课，即「当心不透明性」
and intransparencies of a puzzle is any aspect that is not explained to the solver
一道谜题的不透明性是指任何没有向解谜者解释的任何方面
a hidden rule a hidden goal
比如一个隐藏的规则，一个隐藏的目标
maybe a hidden affordance meaning a hidden thing that the player can do
也许是一个隐藏的能力，比如是玩家可以做的一个隐藏的事情
or a hidden interaction or hidden consequence of a certain interaction
或者是一个隐藏的互动或某一互动的隐藏后果
intransparencies can also come in the form of the inability to perceive or interpret the state of the puzzle
不透明性也能够以无法感知或领会谜题状态的形式出现
（译者注：出自唐纳德·诺曼《设计心理学》，七阶段即：目标、计划、制定、执行、感知、解释、比较）
essentially if you're familiar with the quote unquote “seven stages of action”,
基本上来说，如果你熟悉“行动七阶段理论”的话
which uh I think Donald Norman was the one who initially uh made that a popular idea
我想应该是唐纳德·诺曼（Donald Norman）最初让这一观点流行起来的
any one of those seven stages of action can have a failure
这七个行动阶段中的任何一个都可能出现失败
where due to intransparencies the person trying to perform an action just doesn't understand something right?
由于不透明性，试图执行行动的人会对一些事情不理解
I will show you an example. This is a puzzle I have it right here
我给你们看一个例子，这个谜题我这里有实物
It's called the Ramube Octahedron and this puzzle is a puzzle that you your goal is to try and disassemble it uh
这个谜题被称为“Ramube八面体”，你的目标是拆开它
and sort of get into it and you can kind of like move one of the parts around but you know most of them don't really move
仔细看看，你可以移动其中的一个组件，但大多数你是没法移动的
and if you listen carefully you can hear that there's something going on in the inside of it but you can't see what it is right
而如果你仔细听，你可以听到里面有什么东西在动，但你看不到是什么东西，是吧？
so, this is an example of an intransparencies in a puzzle
所以，这就是一个谜题中的不透明性的例子
um another example would be instructionless puzzles
另一个例子是无指令谜题
um this puzzle on the left is uh from a round of the German national puzzle championship
左边这个谜题是德国全国谜题锦标赛的一个赛题
which is how they select their team for world puzzle championships
他们通过全国锦标赛来选拔参加世界锦标赛的队伍
and they had an instructionless round
他们有一个无指令的比赛轮次
and how it works is you're given an empty sort of input puzzle and then you're given its solution
操作方式是，你有一个空的输入谜题，然后你有它对应的答案
and your goal is to work out what is the rule where this input could lead to this solution
你的目标是找出这个输入对应这个答案的规则是什么
and it's unique there is no other solution to this puzzle
而且规则是唯一的，没有其他规则能满足这个谜题
and sometimes that uniqueness is an important part of discovering what the rules are
而有时这种唯一性是发现规则的重要部分
and then of course they'll give you an actual contest puzzle that you have to solve
然后当然他们会给你一个实际的比赛谜题，你必须（用发现的规则）解决它
and all of this including both discovering the instructions and solving the puzzle you're doing under time pressure
全部这些包括发现规则和解决谜题都是在有时间压力下完成的
in this case the rule is that the number tells you of its four cardinal neighbors in the north south east west direction how many of them are different or how many different numbers are represented there
而这个谜题解出来的规则是，这个数字代表其上下左右相邻格子中有多少种不同的数字
so, a one uh you know this one has two threes next to it. it only has one unique neighbor
因此，这里这个1，它旁边有两个3，所以只有一种
whereas this four has all four of one two three four as its neighbors
而这个4，它旁边有1,2,3,4作为它的邻居
（译者注：《顿悟》为中国开发者制作的游戏，作者B站账号@ ArtlessGames）
another example is this game understand which is a steam game
另一个例子是这个steam游戏《顿悟》
where they give you a bunch of symbols on the grid and you have to figure out the rules
在这个游戏中网格上会有一堆符号，你必须自己弄清楚规则
the witness also has this instructionlessness as a part of sort of the early phase of the game when you're learning what the rules are rather than the later phase of the game where you're solving puzzles using those known rules
《见证者》在早期学习规则的阶段中也有这种无指令谜题，而在后期则用已知的规则来解谜
uh mystery hunt puzzles are basically all instructionless. they tend to give you some input and then find something to solve.
解谜寻宝比赛基本上都是无指令的，他们会给你些输入，然后想办法解出来
this is one from this year's mystery hunt where the input was a picture of a bunch of diagrams of what look like sound devices or digital synthesizers
这是今年解谜寻宝的一道题，输入的内容看起像一堆声音设备或数字合成器的连线图
and you get a bunch of these and then you also get these like random strings of letters some of which are red colored
然后你有一堆这样的图，以及这些随机的字母串，其中一些是红色的
and it turns out that you have to download this software that sort of allows you to put together eurorack style modular synths and put them together this way
最后结果是，你得下载一个软件能让你把Eurorack风格的模块化合成器摆成这样
and they would all make synth noises from popular songs uh you know like a synth from lady gaga or from Eurythmics or from whatever
然后它们会生成一些流行歌曲的合成声音，比如Lady Gaga、Eurythmics的合成音
and then these things on the right corresponded to the melodies that you had to play and then you had to put the melodies together and get a secret message from that
然后右边这些字符串对应着一些旋律，你得把这些旋律放在一起播放，从中得到一个秘密信息
and then there was a whole second part to it
然后接着还有一个完整的第二步
um but the point is that the rules are not given at all
关键点是规则根本就没有给出
and figuring out the rules figuring out what you have to do and getting that aha moment of oh these are songs I have to play them
弄清规则、弄清要做的是，然后会得到一个“啊哈”时刻，哦，这些是我得播放出来的歌曲
that is part of the magic of MIT mystery hunt, is discovering what it is that you have to do
这就是MIT解谜寻宝的魅力所在，就是去发现你要做的事情是什么
and intransparencies can be a huge amount of fun but there are many caveats
不透明性可以带来很多乐趣，但也有许多注意事项
they can cause solvers to become stuck and I’ve heard this called enigma syndrome or a few other things
他们会让解谜者卡住，而且我听说过一种叫“谜题综合征”或类似的东西
where you literally just don't know what to do because you failed to put two and two together
你真的不知道做什么，因为你没能把两部分对应起来
and that tends to be an unfun kind of stuck for many puzzles
对于许多谜题来说，这往往是一种不愉快的卡壳
because you don't necessarily have different approaches or different things to try
因为你不一定有其他不同的方法或东西可以去尝试
there isn't really a recourse for you if you just can't figure out what you need to do
如果你连做什么都不知道的话，那也没什么办法能依靠了
if you're making a linear story based game where the puzzles have to come in sequence
而如果你在制作一个谜题按顺序出现的基于故事的线性游戏
then getting stuck means blocking progression in the game which literally means the player cannot play anymore
那么被卡住就意味着游戏进行不下去了，也就意味着玩家玩不下去了
unless they either look up the solution or cheat
除非他们去找攻略或者作弊
or they just have to quit and come back tomorrow
否则他们就得退出游戏，明天再来了
and some players you know they really don't want to look up the solution right
而对于有些玩家，他们真的不想去看攻略，对吧？
but if they're gonna be uh you know very devout about that then they just can't play the game anymore right
但如果他们（对不看攻略）非常虔诚，那他们就再也玩不了这个游戏了
they literally may just stop there and never play beyond that
他们可能就会在那里停下来，再也玩不了后面部分了
um you can see with the completion statistics of many puzzle games on steam
你可以从steam上很多解谜游戏的完成度统计中看到
especially if they have achievements you can see well
尤其是那些有成就的游戏，你可以看到
oh everybody quit after this achievement because there was a really hard puzzle there that got stuck
噢，所有人在这个成就之后都玩不下去了，因为那里有个非常难的谜题而卡住了
on the other hand, if you're making a linear game and you want to avoid that
而另一方面，如果你在制作一个线性游戏，而你想避免这种情况
you may end up taking every puzzle that is remotely difficult and kind of standing off the difficulty or adding hints
你最后可能会把每一个难度过高的谜题都拿出来，降低难度或者加上提示
and those may make it a less pleasurable experience for some other players that really want the challenge right
而这又会让其他一些真正想要挑战的玩家的体验下降了
so, you're having to balance all of these goals together if you make a linear game
因此，如果你制作一个线性游戏，你必须去平衡所有这些目标
another common complaint is that these intransparencies can feel like an IQ test
另一种常见的抱怨是，这些不透明性会让人感觉在做智商测试
it feels like oh I just have to figure out what the pattern is
这感觉就像，哦，我得弄清楚这模式是什么
and some players don't want that to be their puzzle solving experience
而有些玩家不希望他们的解谜体验是这样的
the resolution of the intransparency is also a one-time reveal
同样，不透明性的解总是一次性的
you can't make a hundred puzzles that are based on one intransparency
你不可能基于一点规则的不透明性，就做出上百个谜题
you have to have a hundred different intransparencies and so it could be hard to come up with that
你得有100个不同的不透明性，所以要想出这样的谜题可能会很难
they're also easily spoiled especially if somebody is playing on live streaming service
不透明性也很容易被剧透，特别是在直播的时候
like twitch one person in the chat can just tell them the answer and then it's all over
比如在Twitch上，一个人在聊天框中直接把答案说了，那一切都结束了
so, intransparencies are often not that great
所以，不透明性往往不是那么的好
and the reverse can also be bad
而反过来的情况也不太好
if the streamer knows what's going on or knows the answer but the audience doesn't
如果主播知道他在做什么或者知道答案，但观众不知道
then they'll just have to constantly explain the rules to them
那么他就必须不断地向他们解释规则
which can make the streaming experience a bit worse
这可能会使直播体验变得糟糕
a very common example is the hidden affordance
一个常见的例子是隐藏的能力
which is where you have some kind of affordance or thing you can do that is not tutorial to you or not told to you
即你有某种能力或能做的事情，但教程没说或者没告诉你
and this is an example from the Wind Waker
这是在《塞尔达传说：风之杖》的一个例子
you get this grappling hook and it sort of tells you how to use it and you can swing on things
你得到了这个钩爪，游戏告诉你如何使用，可以挂在东西上摇摆
um but there is another thing you can do with that and that is when you are swinging you can also stop swinging and climb the rope
但你还可以用它做另一件事，那就是当你摆动时，你也可以停止摆动并爬上绳子
and when I was playing this game, I never even knew you could do this
当我玩的时候，我甚至不知道可以这样做
and the method to do it is actually a little bit counter-intuitive
而做到这一点的方法实际上是有点反直觉的
you have to hold the button that in the top right the ZR button here which basically stops you from swinging
你必须按着这个按钮，就是右上方这个，ZR键，它能让你停止摇摆
and then while holding that you have to press up to climb the rope
然后在按住这个按钮的同时，你要按上键来爬上绳子
um and normally when you press up you press like up and down to swing back and forward and time your swings to move forward
一般情况下，按上下键的操作是会让绳子前后摆动，然后找到时机荡过去
so, there's a second movement assigned to the same button
所以，这里是把另一个动作分配给了同一个按钮
uh and you have to climb up to the top of this rope
你必须爬上绳子顶端
and now it's only required in a couple areas of the game to get a couple of secrets
而现在只有在游戏的几个区域需要这样做来获得一些隐藏秘密
but you know I want 100% the dungeon I want to find all the secrets
但我想要达成100%，想找到所有秘密
so uh it was really annoying to me that this was never explained
所以，这真的有点恼火，因为游戏从来没有解释过这个这一点
and then I just had to figure it out uh and it's counterintuitive
然后我得自己找到解决方法，而这是不符合直觉的
and they also this was a port of the game uh an HD port of the game from the original GameCube to the Wii U
不过这是从原来的NGC移植到Wii U的高清重制版
and so, they had to change the controls. so, they may have not tested it enough
所以，他们不得不改变控制方式，因而可能没有进行足够的测试
they may have not done their focus testing to discover that this was a stuck point
他们可能没有做重点测试来发现这是个会卡住的点
or they might have just left it in because it was only for a couple of puzzles anyway
或者他们可能直接把它留了下来，毕竟这只有几个谜题用到了而已
um but for some players this is very frustrating and it could really make you distrust the developers
但是对于一些玩家来说，这非常令人沮丧，它可能让你就不相信开发者了
and normally you don't see stuff like this in Zelda because it's quite well tested
通常你不会在塞尔达中遇到这样的情况，因为塞尔达的测试做得很好
But in this one case it was really you know there are people online who raged about this quite a bit
但在这个案例中就…网上有很多人对这个问题非常生气
one of the ways you can avoid
有一种可以避免这种情况的方法
that is tip number 16 which is to facilitate experimentation um
那便是第16课，「让玩家方便尝试」
and I will show the Ramube Octahedron again as a way of illustrating this
我再次展示一下“Ramube八面体”，来说明一下这一点
basically, like it's clear that there's something rattling around on the inside of it
基本上来说，很明显它内部有东西在发出声音
and it's clear that if you kind of try to push it this way
而且很明显，如果你试图这样推动（外面的部分）
you can push it a little but it gets stuck
你可以推一下，但会被卡住
and you can listen and you can discover that okay there's some balls on the inside or something moving around
然后你听一听就能发现，好吧，里面有球或者什么东西在移动
and if you move it very slowly and listen
而如果你边缓慢转动它边听
you can even try and hear what is the shape of the cavity inside this puzzle how many balls are there
你甚至可以尝试听出里面内部空腔是什么形状、里面有多少个球
are they in the same cavity or are they not
以及它们是否在同一个空腔里
and you can learn all of these things just by experimenting and slowly moving the thing around in information
你可以通过实验和慢慢转动来了解所有这些东西的信息
so, the intransparency of what's in the middle can be made transparent by your own interaction with the puzzle
所以，通过你与谜题的互动，不透明的东西就能变得透明
um you know and you will in fact discover in this puzzle that there are two balls inside they are in the same chamber
接着你就能发现，这两个球是在同一个空腔中
and that chamber has the shape of an S Tetris piece
而这空腔的形状就像一个S型的俄罗斯方块
and you have to get the balls at the two opposite sides of it because the thing you're pushing down goes in the middle
然后你必须想办法让两个球跑到空腔的两端，因为这样才能把中间的部分推下去
so, you kind of have to do a spin move to get the two balls to the opposite side to push it down
所以你做一个旋转动作，让两个球跑到两端去，然后把它推下去
which is an interesting eureka moment
这是一个有趣的尤里卡时刻
but one that you can actually kind of deductively logic yourself toward, if you experiment with it enough to discover how it works
只要你做了充足的试验就能用逻辑推理的方式得到这一点
a rule of thumb that goes along with this is avoid making experimentation frustrating
与之相关的一个经验法则是，不要让试验过程挫败感太强
I remember as a kid playing link to the past and getting to this boss the helmasaur king
我记得小时候玩《塞尔达传说：众神的三角力量》的时候，遇到一个Boss，Helmasaur King
and this boss is really tough he comes at the end of a long gauntlet of difficult enemies that you have to get through
这个Boss真的难打，你要先打一长串困难的敌人，之后他才出现
and if you die you have to restart the whole dungeon and do it all over again
如果你死了，你就得重打整个地牢
and he is the first boss that you cannot defeat using the sword alone
而他是第一个你无法只用剑就打败的Boss
every other boss up until that point you could just use the sword on them but this guy you have to use the hammer on him first
在这之前所有其他Boss都可以用剑来打，而这个家伙必须先用锤子打
and you know it's the usual zelda trope use the item from that dungeon to defeat the boss of that dungeon
你知道这是塞尔达的惯例，用那个地牢的物品来打败那个地牢的Boss
but this was the first time that that idea was used in this game
但这是在这个游戏中第一次应用这一点
and I remember being so frustrated that I would get to this boss fight him my sword would do nothing
我记得我很沮丧，因为我来到这个Boss面前跟他战斗，我的剑没有任何作用
and I didn't know what to do and I would just die
而我不知道该怎么做，我就这样死了
because this guy just hit so hard
因为这家伙攻击力太高了
and you know I would try that a few times die get frustrated and then not know what to do
我试了几次，死了，感到很沮丧，然后不知道该怎么办
because I wasn't able to easily experiment and figure out what the boss's weak point was
因为我不能很轻易地进行试验来找出Boss的弱点
the experimentation required all of this effort beforehand
要进行试验还是先做前面这些努力
and I remember going to my cousin and begging him to tell me how to beat this boss
然后我记得我去找我表哥，求他告诉我如何过这个Boss
and he told me hit his mask with the magic hammer
他告诉我用魔锤打他的面具
and I still as an assault as an adult remember those exact words that he used
而我现在作为一个成年人，我仍然记得当时他说的每一个字
because as a child this was so pertinent and so salient to me
因为作为一个孩子，这对我来说太重要了
when i'm like fighting this boss and was literally blocked by progressing in the game
当我跟Boss战斗的时候，我基本上游戏完全进行不下去了
because I didn't know that secret and certainly that was a huge eureka moment for me just being told the answer
因为我不知道这个秘密，当然这对我来说是一个巨大的尤里卡时刻，因为我知道了答案
because it was so important to being able to progress in this game
因为这对在游戏中取得进展非常重要
but the thing that caused that frustration was the fact that I couldn't experiment
但造成这种挫败感的原因是我无法进行试验
or at least that experimentation required so much effort that I was never able to get there on my own
或者至少说试验需要付出如此之大的努力，以至于我永远无法靠自己的力量达到目的
another example uh and I love this by the way is the hearthstone puzzle labs
另一个例子，我很喜欢这个，就是《炉石传说》谜题实验室
which was an expansion to the hearthstone uh game made i think a year or two ago
这是《炉石传说》的一个资料片，我想应该是一两年前制作的
um and there are a bunch of these puzzles that you have to solve using hearthstone cards
里面有很多谜题，你必须用《炉石传说》的卡片来解决它们
and they're very interesting very exciting I highly recommend this
这些谜题非常有趣刺激，我非常非常推荐它
even if you've never played hearthstone
即使你从未玩过《炉石传说》
（译者注：砰砰博士清场-谜题3/4-疯狂实验）
um but this particular puzzle uh is a doozy it's called the test
但这个特别的谜题，叫做“疯狂实验”
and there is this unit on the board called the test subject
场上有随从叫“实验体”
and it has the property that whenever it dies it gives you a copy of every spell you've ever played on it
它的特性是每当它死了，就会给你在它身上施放过的所有法术的副本到你的手牌中
and there is also a spell that you have in this called vivid nightmare that copies a minion
还有一个叫做“鲜活梦魇”的法术，它可以复制一个随从
and when you copy a minion it kind of also copies the triggers that are attached to that minion
当你复制一个随从，它也会复制附属于随从的触发效果
so there's this very sophisticated interaction of creating copies of spells via minions that you've copied
所以通过复制随从来复制法术是一种非常复杂的互动
and there are also a bunch of spells that you have that change the health of minions and kill them and do various things
有一堆法术可以改变随从的生命、杀死他们以及做各种事情
um so the solution to this puzzle you know you only have 10 cards in your hand
所以这个谜题的答案是，你知道，你手中只有10张牌
but you actually may end up playing 20 or 30 of them to actually go through with it
但实际上你最终可能要打出20或30张牌来完成它
and for each one of the cards you play you have to sort of watch through its animation sometimes there's voice lines uh
对于每张牌，你都要看它的动画，有时还会有语音台词
and the order of operations is very important and even learning what the priority of things are
而操作的顺序是非常重要的，甚至要去掌握各种优先顺序是什么
like when a death happens in what order do the triggers happen that order of trigger interaction is relevant in this puzzle
比如当死亡发生时，触发效果按什么顺序发生，而这个顺序是与这个谜题相关的
and the first time I solved this puzzle or actually the first time I put together a solution that I thought would solve this puzzle
当我第一次解这个谜题的时候，或者说我第一次打出我认为可以的解
it turned out that it didn't work due to some subtlety of the interactions that I didn't know
结果发现，由于一些我不了解的微妙的相互作用，并没有成功
and this was immensely frustrating but was even more frustrating is that
这让我非常沮丧，但更让我沮丧的是
that thing on the right over there is not an undo button it is a reset button
右边的那个东西不是撤销按钮，而是一个重置按钮
there is no undo in this puzzle and when you reset it clears the whole board
谜题中没有撤消键，当你重置时，整个场上都被清除了
it plays an unskippable eight second animation
它会播放一个不可跳过的八秒动画
there's a voice line that comes from the the boss on the other side who makes fun of you
对面Boss又有段语音来嘲讽你
and uh it's just the experience of experimenting to learn what happens is made very tedious by the interface
只是为了了解发生了什么而进行的试验，被这个界面交互搞得有些厌烦了
and you know hearthstone isn't a puzzle game
你知道《炉石传说》并不是一个解谜游戏
it is it is a game uh that's very much about sort of the charming whimsy of the interaction of these cards in a magical universe
它是一个注重卡牌在一个奇幻宇宙中的互动所带来迷人的奇思妙想的游戏
and those voice lines are part of what makes hearthstone hearthstone
而这些台词也是《炉石传说》之所以成为《炉石传说》的原因之一
uh but in the context of a puzzle game it sort of became very irritating for me to like actually interface with the puzzle itself
但在解谜游戏的背景下，它对我来说变得非常烦躁
um so it's something to keep in mind that if you make experimentation frustrating
所以我们要记住，如果你让试验过程变得充满挫败感
and if you make sort of learning the underlying system of the puzzle difficult or frustrating or place obstacles in front of the player of doing that
如果你让学习谜题的基本机制变得困难或令人沮丧，或者在玩家面前为此设置障碍
then uh the player may never get to the heart of the puzzle and may just give up right
那么，玩家可能永远无法领悟到谜题的核心，可能就会放弃了，对吧？
they won't be uh you know driven to continue playing by the exciting thing around the corner
他们就不会由即将到来的兴奋事物所驱动而继续玩下去
they'll just be like ugh I can't be bothered
他们就会说，唉，我不玩了！
one solution to avoid making experimentation necessary at all is to show the player things that they would otherwise have to find out
一种避免这种试验成为必要的解决方法是，直接向玩家展示他们必须自己发现的东西
don't put a button on the ground and make the player stand on it to see what it does
不要在地方放一个按钮，让玩家得站到上面去看它的作用是什么
put a line next to the button and a little indicator on the wall
而在按钮旁画条线，在墙上放个小指示灯
that can show the player what the puzzle is going to do when they step on it
这能向玩家展示他们踩在上面的时候，谜题会发生什么
this is something that portal did you know a decade and a half ago
十五年前的《传送门》就是这么做的
Ittle Dew does something even more interesting
《Ittle Dew》做了一件更有趣的事
where when you whenever you hit a locked door or a locked gate
当你碰到一个锁着的门时
it will show these little particles that travel from the locked gate to either the buttons on the floor or the switches that you have to hit in order to activate it uh
它就会显示出这些小粒子，从上锁的门到地板上那些用来激活门的按钮或开关
and this removes the need for you to figure out what combination of switches you need to hit to open this door
这样你就不需要再去琢磨该用什么开关组合来打开这扇门了
and games like DROD (Deadly Rooms of Death) also do the same thing
像《DROD》（《死亡密室Deadly Rooms of Death》）这样的游戏也做了同样的事情
so, a related idea is always “try to get the solver on the right path”
因此，相关的一点是「尝试让解谜者走在正确的道路上」
realizing that you're on the right track is one of the most dopaminergic things just in the same way that anticipating you know a eureka moment being right around the corner
意识到你走对路了是最能激发多巴胺的事情之一，就像你期待即将到来的尤里卡时刻一样
is really interesting sort of being on the right track
走在正确道路上的那种感觉真的很有趣
and being told that you're on the right track is similarly very motivating
而被告知你在正确的道路上能给你很大的动力
uh in American crosswords every letter is checked
比如在美国填字游戏中，每个字母都可被检查
meaning that every letter exists in both the horizontal and vertical word
也就是说，每个字母都同时存在于横排和竖排的单词中
and when you get that confirmation and ah yes this is the same letter when I’ve solved both of these clues
当你得到确认，“对了，我把两个都解出来了，这个字母是一样的”
it gives you this sort of satisfaction that you're moving forward that you're making correct progress
你就会有一种满足感，你在前进、在取得正确的进展
many crossword clues they may have multiple possible answers right
而许多填字游戏的谜面都可能对应多个答案，对吗？
there may be multiple possible words that are four letters long and satisfy this clue
可能有多个长为4个字母的词可以满足这个谜面的要求
but as we've sort of seen in some of the earlier examples only one of them is correct
但正如我们在前面的一些例子中看到的那样，只有一个是正确的
and you may not know which one it is until you get this confirmer
你可能不知道是哪一个，直到你得到这个确认物
but the confirmer is sort of a push to keep going and motivation to understand that you're on the right track
而这个确认物是一种推动力，让你继续前进，让你明白方向是正确的
um Cryptics actually do this within individual clues
Cryptic填字游戏在每一个谜面中都是这样做的
so, uh in crypted crosswords if you don't know every clue actually contains both a literal definition and a sort of pun or cryptic definition
在Cryptic填字游戏中每条谜面都包含了一个字面解释和一个类似双关或字谜的解释
so, you might see a seven letter word for terrain scrambled coach
所以你会看到这样一个对应7个字母单词的谜题“Terrain Scrambled Coach”
and you split it down the middle a coach is a trainer
你把它从中间分开，Coach就是Trainer（教练）
but the word terrain scrambled i.e. anagrams is also the word trainer
而“Terrain Scrambled”（把Terrain打乱），
也就是说Terrain的同字母异构词，也是Trainer
so, within every individual clue, you have a confirmer because you have two sides of it that make the answer
所以在每个谜面中都有一个确认物，因为你可以从两方面佐证答案
and sometimes when you're solving a cryptic you won't necessarily solve both of them
有时你解出一个谜题，你不一定是同时从两面都解开的
like you might solve the literal clue and not solve the other one and sort of check it by the letter crossings
比如你可能只解出了字面意义，然后通过字母交叉来检查
Cryptics have fewer letter crossings than American crosswords
Cryptic填字游戏比美国填字游戏的字母交叉要少一些
um but sometimes the answer kind of reveals what the pun was and can create this exciting moment of
答案还是会显示出这对应的双关是什么，并能够创造出这种令人兴奋的时刻
oh, is get it it's terrain scrambled
“哦，我明白了，这是把Terrain打乱”
um you know so it provides additional sparkle
所以它提供了额外的Sparkle
uh whoops okay we're back
噢，黑屏了，好的，我们又回来了
uh let's see um puzzle hunts often also have confirmers
解谜寻宝通常也有确认物
where sometimes you know you're halfway through a puzzle and you got somewhere
有时你知道你做到一半了，感觉到了某个阶段了
and you know you think maybe is this the answer and then you type it into the answer box
你觉得可能这就是答案吧，然后把它输入到答案框中
and instead of saying good job you solve the puzzle it says keep going
它不会说“做的不错，你解开了谜题”，而是说“继续吧”
and what keep going means in that context is that that's not the answer
在这种情况下，意思就是这还不是答案
it's another clue it's something that you can move forward on in a different direction something new you have to try
而是另一条线索，你可以据此朝不同方向前进、尝试些新东西
uh but that can also be very motivating
但这也是非常有动力的
because it means everything you've done up until now was something that was intended for you to do
因为这意味着你到现在为止所做的一切，都是你应当做的
（译者注：红鲱鱼Red Herring：转移注意力的事物）
a related question that I often get is “are red herrings bad? should you avoid them?”
我经常被问及的一个相关问题是“红鲱鱼（Red Herring）好不好？你应该避免它们吗？”
and I mean this is a very complicated subject
这是一个非常复杂的问题
there are a lot of different types of red herrings and whether or not they're bad is very situational
有很多不同类型的红鲱鱼，它们是否有害得看情况
a dressing is the name for sort of a needless non-pertinent decoration that's salient enough that the solver might accidentally interpret it as pertinent
Dressing（装饰）是指，一种本身不必要的、与谜题无关的装饰物，
但又足够突出明显以至于会让解谜者意外地将其理解为与谜题相关
in chess puzzles for example if you just add extra pieces that are not relevant to the solution and don't prevent any wrong solutions from being relevant
比如，在棋谜中，你添加了几个与解谜无关的棋子进去，也没有阻止任何与之相关的错误解法
then those are considered dressings
那这些就被看做是Dressing
and they're often frowned upon
通常它们（dressing）是不可取的
because they may distract the solver from what they actually need to do
因为它们可能会分散解谜者的注意力，使他们无法完成真正的任务
same thing in escape rooms like people often want to decorate the escape room and make it look nice
密室逃脱也是如此，人们经常想装饰一下密室，让它看起来漂亮点
but uh you know players may see bars in a jail and try
但玩家可能会比如说，他看到了类似监狱的铁栏杆
and you know count them and put that as a number in some combination lock right
就会去数一数有多少个栏杆，然后把它作为数字输入密码锁，对吧？
like you gotta really make sure that uh your dressings are not interpreted as pertinent
你真的得保证你做的这些装饰不会被理解为相关的东西
distractors are affordances that you never need
干扰项是你永远不需要的能力或事物
um you know there's there's an example like make 35 cents with 10 coins and the quarter is not needed
比如说，用10个硬币凑成35美分，那么面值25分的硬币肯定是不需要的
therefore it is a distractor it's an affordance that you didn't need
因此，它是一个干扰项，是一个你不需要的事物
but it sort of feels like it should be there right?
但总感觉它也应该被放在那里，对吗？
it's not it's not a red herring that's going to confuse you
它不是那种会让你感到困惑的红鲱鱼
you know fake puzzles and ghost puzzles are things that come up in escape rooms
至于假谜题和幽灵谜题，则是在密室逃脱中
where you see something that looks like a puzzle but it turns out not to be
那些看起来像谜题却不是的东西
a ghost puzzle is a puzzle that used to be in the room and then was removed
幽灵谜题是曾经设置在密室中的谜题，而后来被移走了
but somehow there's some little bit of it that's left that wasn't cleaned up
但还有一些没有被清理感觉的东西留在房间里
you might just see a shadow on the wall of where something was
你可能会在墙上看到曾经某个东西的影子
or you might see some parts of what used to be a puzzle
或者看到曾经是谜题的一部分的东西
but they've been disconnected and are no longer part of the solution
但它们实际上是没关联的，不再是解的一部分了
every escape room fan will tell you that they've seen these
每个密室逃脱爱好者都会告诉你，他们见到过这种东西
and they get so mad when that wasn't taken out of the room
当他们知道了这是没被拿干净的东西，会非常生气
because they'll spend their time which in escape room is precious you only have an hour to get out
因为他们为此浪费了时间，而在密室逃脱中，时间非常宝贵，你只有一个小时逃离
they'll spend their time trying to figure out what to do with that thing and if it turns out oh you didn't have to do anything it wasn't part of the puzzle
他们会花时间去想怎么处理那个东西，结果根本不需要做什么，它就不是谜题的一部分
then that really irritates people it feels like they've been robbed of their time
那就真的很让人生气了，感觉时间被剥夺了
obfuscation and misdirection come in many forms and can be sometimes interpreted as red herrings
混淆和误导有很多形式，有时可以被理解为红鲱鱼
but sometimes it's more like uh showing the solver what is a non-solution so that they can appreciate the solution more, right?
但有时它又更像是在向解谜者展示什么不是解法，而这样他们会更欣赏真正的解法，对吗？
there's various ways that misdirection can actually be good, so you don't want to rule that out as bad
有很多种误导的方式可以是好事情，所以你不要把它都当作不好的东西移除掉
dead end approaches are any approach that you might try to solve a puzzle that immediately leads to a negative confirmer
“死胡同方法”是那种，你一尝试就马上会给你一个负面确认的解谜方法
meaning meaning you try something and then you learn
意识就是说，你尝试了些东西
oh this cannot be the approach this cannot possibly work there is a clear dead end to here
然后你就了解到，噢，肯定不是这个方法，肯定不行，明显是走不通的
the opposite is a rabbit trail which is an incorrect approach to solving a puzzle that cannot be proven not to work
与之相反的则是Rabbit Trail（兔子足迹），指的是错误的解谜方法，但却没法被证明是不可行
um you know you might be in some block-pushing game
比如可能在一些推箱子游戏中
and it turns out you have to do this one thing but you're trying this other thing
结果你本来应该要做这样的事，但你却一直在尝试别的事情
and it seems like you're maybe making progress and you're trying a few more things
而你又似乎在取得进展，然后你又继续尝试
and you know it's just branching and getting deeper and maybe you're making progress maybe you're not
然后你越来越深入，你感觉你可能有进展也可能没有
but an hour later you're still trying that one thing and you haven't quite got to the exit
但一小时之后，你还在尝试那件事情，还没有走到出口
and maybe it's impossible right but but you don't know you don't have an obvious proof that's impossible
或许这确实是不可能的，但你没有一个明显的证据证明它不可能
so you waste an hour trying something that isn't the intended or correct solution
所以你浪费了一个小时的时间去尝试了一些不是预期的或正确的解法
rabbit trails are the most demotivating especially for novices
Rabbit Trails是最令人沮丧的，特别是对新手来说
because novices are not particularly good at guessing what will work or guessing what the intended solution method to a puzzle will be
因为新手并不擅长猜测什么是可行的，或者猜测谜题的预期解法是什么
they may spend a long time and only change their approach when they've really just given up and been beaten down into thinking
他们可能花很长的时间，然后只有在他们真正放弃了或者被打败了才会改变自己的方法
well you know I don't want to try this anymore
你知道“我不想再尝试这个了”
to address this like really sealing off rabbit trails is a good idea
要对付这种问题，把Rabbit Trails完全封锁住是一个不错的想法
if you're playtesting something and you notice that players are spending a long time trying an approach that doesn't work
如果你在测试的时候，注意到玩家花费了很长时间去尝试一个行不通的方法
you should probably either prevent them from trying it
那也许你应该阻止他们去尝试这种方法
or add a negative confirmer of some kind you know go back this isn't the solution not like this try something else
或者加入些负面确认物，比如说“回去吧，不是这么做的，试试别的”
and to discover those you really need to playtest it
而要发现这些问题，你真的得去做测试才行
the sort of lesson expressed in four words is “match pertinence with salience “
用四个词来总结这个经验就是“让相关性与显著性相匹配”
pertinence meaning things that are relative to the actual solution of the puzzle
相关的事物指与实际的解法有关的东西
things that are either clueful or are affordances that you need or are interactions that you need to do
这些东西要么提供线索，要么是你需要或需要交互的能力与物品
and salience meaning how much something sticks out how clear is it to the player that this is important how important looking is something
显著性则是指某一事物有多么突出，玩家看起来它有多么重要
things that are important should stick out
重要的东西应该是突出的
things that stick out should be important
突出的东西应该是重要的
you do not want to have negatives in either direction
你不希望出现与之相反的情况
you don't necessarily well you don't want to have important things that are subtle
你不会希望重要的东西看起来不明显
or at least are more subtle than everything else in the environment
或者至少比环境中的其他所有东西都更不明显
and you don't want to have things that stick out and look like they might be clueful or might be puzzly that turn out not to be
你也不希望会有很突出的东西，看起来像线索、与谜题相关，结果却不是
and keep in mind that video game players especially who are not necessarily experts at puzzles
请记住，尤其是电子游戏玩家，他们不一定是解谜的专家
they may not have the conventions in place that allow them to determine what is clueful
他们可能没有约定俗成的惯例，来让他们判断什么是线索
like when you're solving an escape room and you've done 50 of them
就假设你是个玩过50多次密室逃脱的老手
you probably can guess whether or not something is clueful
你可能会猜到某个东西是不是线索
if you're doing a mystery hunt puzzle and you've done hundreds of them
假设你玩过上百次解谜寻宝
and you see something you can probably guess whether or not that's supposed to be a clue
你看到一个东西，你能大概猜到这应不应该是个线索
or whether it's supposed to be just you know flavor text flavor art not relevant
或者它是不是只是无关的文字或图片
but newer players are not able to make that distinction uh especially in video games
但新玩家是无法做出区分的，特别是在电子游戏中
because video games have conventions that change so much from genre to genre
因为不同类型的电子游戏之间的惯例差别变化很大
that it's it's very hard to play for players to know what they know
所以玩家很难知道自己知道什么
or know what they're expected to know
或者很难知道他们应该知道什么
or know what the game designer is expecting them to interpret
或者很难知道游戏设计者希望他们如何去理解
so always try to match pertinence with salience as much as you can
所以要尽可能地使相关性和显著性相匹配
next lesson is to “seek depth in systems and rule sets”
下一课是「追求系统与规则集的深度」
this is a lesson that comes from physical puzzle games
这是一个来自实体解谜游戏的经验
uh particularly those published by um publishers like think fun and smart games
特别是那些由像Think Fun和Smart Games这样的发行商发行的游戏
they have this interesting method of putting together physical puzzles rather than getting just you know one puzzle like one of these that you buy
他们有一种有趣的方法来构建实物解谜游戏，而不是像你买的那种只有一个谜题的游戏
they have a kit that comes with different items that you can put together
他们有一套工具包，里面有不同的物品，你可以把它们组合起来
and then they'll have a booklet or a set of cards that contain challenges
然后他们会有一本小册子或一套包含挑战的卡片
and each puzzle will come with say 50 to 100 different challenges of increasing difficulty
每套谜题都会有50到100个不同的挑战，难度不断增加
almost in the same kind of progression that you would see in a traditional video game um
几乎就与你在电子游戏中看到的那种难度逐渐增加相同
and so, rush hour you're sort of moving these cars around you have to get the red car out of the grid
所以比如《Rush Hour》里面，你要移动这些红车，来让它们从格子中走出来
and there's just 50 different configurations of obstacles for it um each of which you have to solve
有50种不同的障碍物的布局配置可供你来解决
and so, it's a nice experience for somebody buying these
所以对于购买这些游戏的人来说，这是一种很好的体验
because they're sort of more content it's not just one puzzle
因为他们有更多的内容，不仅仅是一个谜题
it also can make manufacturing much cheaper because you sort of have to just make the set of parts once and then make the 50 puzzles
这也可以使生产成本大大降低，因为你只需要制作一次部件，然后设计50个谜题
uh the cards are really cheap to make 50 of and you don't have to make 50 copies of the game board
制作50张卡片是很便宜的，不需要把游戏的实物制作50份
it also allows the player to have a conceptual model
它还让玩家有一个概念模型
meaning develop a sophisticated understanding of what the pieces are how the work how they move how they work how they move around
意味着玩家对各个组件如何工作、如何移动构建起一套复杂巧妙的理解
once you have a eureka moment or a discovery of an emergent consequence of that system
一旦你有了一个尤里卡时刻，或者发现了这个系统的一个涌现结果
you can reuse that knowledge in future puzzles
你就可以在未来的谜题中复用这些知识
and puzzles can therefore build upon one another with increasingly complicated sort of lemmas and templates and theorems
因此谜题可以在先前谜题的基础上，使用越来越复杂的理论和模型来建立
that the player can learn as they're solving this puzzle
玩家可以在解决这些谜题的过程中学到这些知识
and as they develop a more and more detailed model of what are the consequences of this system
并对这个系统的结果形成越来越详细的模型
so, you get depth and you also get consistency in the design
所以，你会得到深度，也会得到设计的一致性
and the emergent surprises can be much much deeper than just some sort of one-off on the surface trick
并且涌现的惊喜也比那种一次性的、比较浅薄的谜题深得多
you know something something like the Ramube Octahedron and that's sort of one trick that you can use one time
比如说像《Ramube八面体》这样的东西就是一次性的技巧
but in systems-based puzzles you can have many different tricks that arise from the same situation
但在基于系统的谜题中，你可以在同一情景下由许多不同的技巧
this can make the eureka moment sort of more exciting because they're more surprising
这可以让尤里卡时刻更加激动人心，因为它们更加令人惊喜
because there's more depth behind them
因为它们背后有更多的深度
they can also reduce the cost of content creation
它们还可以降低内容创作的成本
because you know you only have to make one of these cards
因为你知道你只需要做一张这样的卡片
and designing a new instance of a puzzle is often a lot less difficult than designing a new rule set or a new gimmick for a new puzzle completely
设计一个谜题的新实例往往比为一个全新的谜题设计一套规则集容易得多
I’ll give you another example which is from Thomas Snyder
我再给你举个例子，这来自Thomas Snyder
he's a three-time world sudoku champion world puzzle champion
他是三届世界数独冠军、世界谜题锦标赛冠军
he's the founder of grand master puzzles
他是Grand Master Puzzle的创始人
which is a company that publishes a puzzle blog as well as many puzzle books and puzzle magazines
这是一个出版谜题博客、谜题书籍和谜题杂志的公司
he's also a mentor to many people on topics relating to puzzle design
他也是许多人在谜题设计方面的导师
he's an advisor on my latest project uh
他是我最新项目的顾问
he has this idea which he's described to me as sort of the capacity of a puzzle
它有这样一个观点，他向我描述了一个类似谜题的“容量”之类的东西
or the the um the sort of space available to in within a certain puzzle type to express ideas of that puzzle
或者说是在特定谜题类型下，可用来表达该谜题想法的空间
and the way he describes it is in two different ways which are equivalent
它用了两种等价的方式来描述的：
how many can you create of this puzzle type before you start repeating the same tricks over and over again
“在你开始重复同样的技巧之前，你能创造出多少个这种类型的谜题？”
like say you're doing sudoku, how many sudoku's can you make before the solution to the sudoku's is just going to have no new ideas
假设说你在创作数独，在数独的解法没有了新的概念之前，你能设计出多少个数独
and the answer is it's probably somewhere between 50 and 100 it might be like 80 sudokus
答案是可能在50到100之间，可能是80个左右
he also describes it as how many of this puzzle type he would actually want to do in his life
他的另一种描述是，他这一生中对这种谜题类型他真正想做多少个？
like say somebody made the perfect puzzle book of sudoku puzzles
假设说有人创作了一本完美的数独谜题书
let's say and you know tried to include all of the interesting sudoku tricks in there but not really repeat them much
假设他试图把所有有趣的数独技巧都包含在里面，但又不重复它们
you know how many puzzles would that book have in it
你知道那本书里会有多少道谜题吗
it's not a thousand sudoku puzzles it's much less
肯定是没有一千道的，会少很多
and different puzzle types have different capacities
而且不同的谜题类型有不同的容量
you know a simple two-dimensional maze you know you can do one of them and then you sort of learn well okay follow the right-hand side or whatever
一个简单的二维迷宫，你可能做一次就知道要按照右手原则之类的
there's not that much to do
没有那么多事情可做
something like a portal gun may only really support 10 different unique eureka moments
像传送门枪这样的东西可能只支持10个不同的尤里卡时刻
sudoku might be more like a hundred
数独可能更像有100个
and a game like the witness could be 10 times that
而像《见证者》这样的游戏可以是这个数字的10倍
just because it has so many different uh components that can go into those puzzle systems
只是因为它里面能够加入到谜题系统的组件有非常多
different rules different uh symbols and constraints within each puzzle
每个谜题里面还有不同的规则、不同的符号、不同的约束
go problems might be the deepest of them
围棋谜题可能是这些里面最深的
all I think there are people who've solved ten thousand go puzzles or more
我认为有些已经做了一万多个围棋谜题
and are still finding unique and interesting ideas in new puzzles that they haven't seen before
但仍然能在新的谜题中发现他们以前没有见过的独特而有趣的想法
and that's something a bit unique and remarkable about the game of go
这就是围棋的独特之处，也是围棋的非凡之处
whose rules are very simple but somehow there's this unexpected depth there
围棋的规则非常简单，但却有意想不到的深度
where you can express tens of thousands of different ideas using the sort of basic uh go rules um
你可以用基本的围棋规则表达数以万计的不同想法
you know you might think are there really only 10 portal gun puzzles
你可能会想，传送门枪真的只能对应10个不同的谜题吗？
like portal had more levels than that right? like aren't there more ideas than that
《传送门》里的关卡可比这多得多，是吧？不是应该会有更多的想法吗？
well I mean I’m talking about just the basic sort of portal gun and walls
其实我的意思是，我说的只是类似于传送门枪与墙之间的基本（的技巧）
there's not that many things you can do with it
你能做的其实并没有那么多
like there's traversal there's some line of sight shooting tricks
比如说直接传送、沿直线打出传送门
you can put a portal on the ceiling
比如往天花板上打传送门
there's the momentum conservation trick
还有（进出传送门）动量守恒的技巧
there's a lot of tricks where you sort of move one portal but leave another
还有些技巧比如说你固定一个传送门，但改变另一个传送门
in order to be able to get back to a place where you were before
以便你就能回到之前的地方
but very quickly you start running out of ideas to make truly unique puzzles
但是很快你就开始耗尽能制作独特谜题的想法了
and then you start to add you know you need to add new components
然后你就会开始添加新的组件
the death pits and the missile turrets
比如掉进去就会死的水潭、发射导弹的塔
and the companion cubes and the buttons you can push them on
还有同伴方块、你可以按的按钮
and then in portal 2 they add the light bridges and the anti-gravity spirals
然后在传送门2中他们增加了光桥和反重力光柱
and the the the paint that you can paint on the walls to make them portable
还有那种能涂到墙上的涂料，能让传送门打上去
and the bouncy colored goop that you can speed off of and bounce on
还有加速和增强弹跳的凝胶
you know these new components are what's adding additional capacity to the puzzles to be able to express more unique eureka moments
这些新组件为谜题增加了额外的容量，能够表达更多独特的尤里卡时刻
but just the raw ingredients uh are not really that uh
但原始成分并没有那么（多）
they can't speak to that many eureka moments there's just not that much there
它们无法表达那么多的尤里卡时刻，没有那么多东西
and what logic puzzle folks do is they often create hybrids and variants
搞逻辑解谜的人所做的是，他们会创作一些混合体和变体
these are all sort of variations on sudoku
这些都是数独的变体
you can see here there's one where the regions are not square there's a hex grid
你可以看到这个网格不是正方形的，是六边形的网格
there's a 3D-ish grid or sort of on the surface of this isometric cube
有个看起来像3D网格的，或者说类似于正交视角下立方体表面上的网格
um and then increasingly complex variations uh or hybrids as they are often called
然后就是越来越复杂的变体，或者他们把它叫做混合体
where you're blending one type of puzzle like sudoku with another type like a domino puzzle
就是你把一种类型的谜题比如数独和另一种类型的谜题如骨牌谜题融合在一起
and through hybrids and variations you can sort of have limitless variety and endless eureka moments
通过混合体和变体，你可以有无限的多样性和无尽的尤里卡时刻
uh because each of these puzzles sort of has its own rules and its own consequences and its own emergent complexity or lemmas that arise from that set of rules
因为这些谜题都有各自的规则、各自的结果、各自的涌现复杂性或者说从规则中产生的规律
there are some sort of common tropes in these
这些（增加容量的谜题）都有些常用的方法
changing geometry or topology
一是改变几何结构或拓扑结构
moving from you know flat geometry to a cylinder or a torus
比如说从平面几何图形到圆柱体或环面
moving from a square grid to triangle or hex or whatever other grid type you want
从正方形网格到三角形或六角形或其他网格类型
adding new constraints and clue types
增加新的约束条件和线索类型
combining two puzzle types together
将两种类型的谜题结合在一起
liar clues you know exactly one of these clues is wrong, there's a wolf in sheep's clothing somewhere
“撒谎线索”，比如那种“这些线索中恰好有一条是错的”，有个披着羊皮的狼
cipher clues where you replace numbers in a grid with a set of letters and each letter corresponds to a unique number
密码线索，你用一组字母替换网格中的数字，每个字母对应一个唯一的数字
（译者注：这个名字没听出来，望指正）
off-by-one or ??? as it's often called uh where every number in the grid is off by one you know a three could be either a two or a four
“偏置1”或者更常见的名字叫（？），网格中每个数字都加减1，比如3可能就是2或4
you know these are common ideas you'll see over and over again in logic puzzles
这些都是你会在逻辑解谜中反复见到的常见想法
and they add a lot of depth and complexity sort of new eureka moments um
而它们增加了很多深度和复杂性、增加了新的尤里卡时刻
there's this question like where does depth come from in certain types of puzzle systems
有这样一个问题：在特定类型的谜题系统中，深度从何而来？
somehow go is inherently deep
不知何故，围棋天然就有很深的深入
and it's very difficult to understand why it is so deep
而且很难理解为什么它如此有深度
there is this computational complexity answer which is like oh you know a go is np-complete or PSPACE-complete if you're familiar with complexity theory
如果你熟悉复杂度理论的话，有这么个计算复杂度的答案，
即围棋是NP完全的以及PSPACE完全的
and that sort of represents that go can sort of encode other types of puzzles which are increasingly complex
这类似于说围棋可以编码其他类型的谜题，而这些谜题越来越复杂
and that may be true but often uh the way you represent something very complex
这也许是对的，但通常情况下你表示非常复杂的东西的方式是
is like you know building a circuit out of go stones and then like this circuit is only satisfiable if you know player white wins in this go situation
可能是你构造一个谜题说用围棋棋子围个什么圈，然后在这种情况下只有白棋赢才能满足
and those can be very contrived
而这些人为构造的痕迹就太强了
what's unique about go is that it's complex even with relatively simple constructions
围棋的独特之处就在于，即使是相对简单的构造，也能体现它很复杂
of you know a little puzzle that takes up one quarter of a go board or less um without necessarily a lot of contrivance right
比如一个只占棋盘四分之一或更少的谜题也能体现，不需要太多的人为构造，对吧？
games like hearthstone have huge amount of contrivance to their puzzles
像《炉石传说》这样的游戏，其中的谜题就有大量的人为构造
because there's thousands of cards in the game you'll never run out of puzzles to create because there's just so many cards there
因为游戏中有数千张牌，你永远不会没有谜题可做，因为里面有很多牌
and some games like the witness or baba is you
还有一些游戏，比如《见证者》或《Baba Is You》
they get away with the interaction between the different rules and constraints giving you this emergent complexity
它们则是通过不同规则和约束之间的互动，来带这种涌现的复杂度
you know you may have uh n different rules but there are sort of two to the n different ways that those can be combined together
比如你共有n个不同规则，但你有2的n次方种不同方式把它们结合起来
and so you sort of you know there are n squared ways for example that you can take a pair of rules and combine them
又比如说即使你只取一对规则出来结合，也有n平方种方式
but sometimes even three or more will give you unique emergent eurekas
但有时三个或更多规则结合会来带独特的涌现的尤里卡
that don't exist with two or less of the rules combined
这在两种规则结合或更少的情况下是不存在的
especially in a game like baba is you where sometimes you need five rules put together
特别是像《Baba Is You》这样的游戏，有时你需要五条规则组合在一起
and then something magical can happen
然后会有神奇的事情发生
level geometry is another thing that can give you really interesting deep emergent interactions
关卡几何结构是另一种可以给你带来很有趣的深层涌现交互的东西
a few examples of this one is steven's sausage roll
一个例子是《史蒂芬香肠卷》
which is a game where you're running around as this little character with a fork skewering sausages pushing them around picking them up
游戏里面你作为一个小角色拿车叉子到处怼香肠，把它们推来推去、叉起来
and later you know dragging them up ladders and doing interesting contortions with with your body and various other things
带上梯子、用你的身体和其他各种东西做有趣的扭曲动作
which uh um you know I almost don't want to spoil them because they're magical
我真的不太想剧透，因为它们很神奇
I know i've been spoiling a lot of stuff in this talk
你知道我在这个讲座中已经剧透了太多东西了
when you're talking about puzzle design you inevitably have to spoil things
当你在谈论谜题设计时，你不可避免地会剧透一些东西
um but this is a game that is worth playing uh to the end
不过这确实是一个值得玩到最后的游戏
or you know at least learning all of the things that it does
或者你至少得了解它里面所做的所有事情
uh because it's so remarkable
因为它真的太棒了
like like there's no new items you pick up when you're playing steven sausage roll
就像说你玩《史蒂芬香肠卷》的时候，并不会去捡到新的物品
you don't open a chest and get the hook shot or the power glove
你不会打开个箱子，然后得到钩爪或者动力手套
you know it's all just the base movement of the game
游戏里面都只是些基本的移动操作
two other games that are similar are pipe push paradise and a monsters expedition
另外两个类似的游戏是《推管天堂》和《怪兽远征》
where you really just have a sort of a simple move and push type of mechanic
在里面你真的只有类似简单移动和推动的机制
but a lot of emergent complexity via the interactions that happen with the objects
但通过物体之间的互动带来了很多涌现复杂度
you know in pipe push paradise you can sort of push pipes down into holes and roll them over while a piece of them goes into a hole and then comes back out
比如《推管天堂》中，你可以把管子推到洞里，然后翻过来，让一部分进入洞里再弄出来
uh in a monster's exposition you're rolling a log over another log and then pushing them into the water and then while in the water there's different things you can do with them
在《怪兽远征》中，你可以把一个木头滚到另一个上，然后推到水里，然后做各种各样的事
it's uh quite an interesting experience and both of these games are massive rabbit holes to go down
这些都是很有趣的体验，而这两个游戏都有很深的深度
and monster's expedition has i like 500 600 i don't know how many levels
《怪兽远征》大概有五六百个关卡吧，我不记得有多少了
it has a lot of levels, hundreds of them um containing dozens and dozens of unique ideas
上百个吧，里面含有数十种独特的想法
that are all consequences of basically just moving cylinders around
基本上都是移动圆柱体所带来的不同结果
and if you have a sufficiently complex system then just through changing the shape of levels
如果你有一个足够复杂的系统，那么仅仅通过改变关卡的形状
you can allow the player to experience all of these different things you can do without adding too much in the way of new mechanics or new things
你就可以让玩家体验到所有这些不同的事情，而不需要增加太多的新机制或新东西。
I mean all of these games do have new mechanics and new things right
当然，我是说所有这些游戏都会有新的机制和东西，对吧？
steven's sausage roll at some point adds in ladders
《史蒂芬香肠卷》游玩到一定进度会加入梯子
pipe push paradise at some point adds in the ability to rotate a pipe
《推管天堂》加入了旋转管道的能力
monster's expedition at some point adds in uh rocks of different heights
《怪兽远征》加入了不同高度的石头
uh but it doesn't add too much of them, there's a very low amount of new things
但并没增加太多，新东西的数量非常少
whereas some puzzle games every five puzzles they give you you know a new toy to play with or a new uh ability to use
而有些解谜游戏每过五个谜题就会给你个新玩具或新能力来使用
these games are very minimal on that and instead try to explore the space of available ideas or or consequences of those ideas as much as possible
前面那些游戏在这方面做得尽量少，而是尽可能去探索可用的想法或这些想法的结果空间
most of the sort of common puzzle tropes that you see over and over again in puzzle games are there because they combine two things
大多数这种解谜游戏的惯用手法，它们会反复出现，是因为它们结合了两件事
one is they're actually hard they they're sort of np-hard or pspace hard or have some kind of actual complexity theoretic hardness to them
一是它们实际上是很难的，它们是那种NP完全或PSPACE完全的，在复杂度理论上很难的
meaning they can encode many hard problems
意味着它们可以编码许多困难的问题
but they also they aren't too chaotic and random
但它们也不是太混乱和随机的
they're things that humans can reason about and facilitate uh deeper understanding of
它们是人类可以推理的东西，并促进更深入的理解
you know connectivity and paths human brains are just great at seeing when things are touching when they're adjacent
像比如说连通性和路径问题，当事物邻接或相邻的时候人类大脑是很善于看到这一点的
you know when this blob is one thing instead of two things
比如当你看到这一片东西是一个东西而不是两个的时候
packing or covering like shapes mental rotation to fit things together
装箱问题和覆盖问题，比如说在脑海中想象形状的旋转以互相匹配
perspective or line of sight sort of 3d geometry of when something can’t be seen from something else
透视或视线这样的三维几何学问题，比如某些东西被其他东西挡住而看不见
these are all things that human brains are just naturally good at reasoning about
这些都是人类大脑天生擅长推理的东西
logic gates and state manipulation
还有逻辑门和状态处理
these are just you know good examples of ways to get complexity in puzzle games
这些都是在解谜游戏中获得复杂性的好例子
but also allow the puzzles to be things that have exciting eureka moments that humans can discover
同时也能够让谜题成为人类能够发现的激动人心的尤里卡时刻
um next lesson is to “understand your puzzle’s state space”
下一课是「理解你的谜题的状态空间」
and this lesson comes to us via a puzzle designer this is um his name is Oskar van Deventer
而这一课是来自一位谜题设计师，他叫Oskar van Deventer
and uh he makes a lot of different types of physical puzzles twisty puzzles uh
他做了很多不同类型的实体谜题，那种转动的智力玩具
he prototypes themselves with a 3d printer
他用3D打印机来制作原型
（译者注：油管频道@OskarPuzzle）
he's got a YouTube channel which is quite interesting to check out
他有一个YouTube频道，很有意思
he's very prolific
他相当高产
this is a puzzle that he worked on which is published by a company called Hanayama puzzles
这是他做的一个谜题，由一家叫Hanayama Puzzles的公司出版
it's the “cast H&H” they're these two h-shaped pieces which can kind of be stuck together and roll around one another in these interesting 3d way ways
这个谜题叫《Cast H&H》，这两块H型部分可以拼在一起，绕着对方以有趣的三维方式转动
the goal is to separate the two pieces but to do this requires a huge number of moves
目标是把这两部分分开，但要做到这一点需要大量的操作
and Oskar actually published the state diagram of this puzzle
而Oskar把这个谜题的状态图发布了出来
these are sort of all the different configurations that these two pieces can be in
这些是这两部分能够出现的所有不同结构
and the lines represent possible transitions from those states
而连线代表状态之间可能的转移
so, wherever there is a line it means you can get the two puzzle pieces from that one state to the other one
所以，只要有一条线，就意味着你可以把这两部分从一个状态移到另一个状态上
and when there isn't a line it means that somehow that transition has been blocked either by a little nubby of the puzzle a little piece of metal that kind of just prevents you from uh making that transition
而没有连线的话，就意味着这个转移被阻挡了，可能是被玩具上一个小疙瘩或一块金属挡住了
and therefore finding a solution to this puzzle is equivalent to finding a path through this graph from in to out along these edges
因此，找到这个谜题的答案就相当于找到一条在图中从IN到OUT的一条路径
and creating this puzzle was basically a task of like snipping certain edges
而创作这个谜题的任务基本上就是去裁剪掉一些边
until the graph that remained was an interesting maze to navigate
直到剩下的图成为一个有趣的迷宫
that didn't have too many dead ends but also had some trails for you to wander down which may or may not lead you to the correct thing uh
里面既没有太多死胡同，但也有些支路给你走，这些支路可能不会把你带到正确的地方
I’ll show you another example from Sokoban
我再给你看个推箱子的例子
This is a paper by Petr Jarušek and Radek Pelánek
这是Petr Jarušek和Radek Pelánek的一篇论文
and in this puzzle they take a bunch of instances of Sokoban and they diagram their state space using a sort of node and edge graph representation
在这篇论文中，他们考察了一些推箱子的实例，并用图来表示它们的状态空间
where each node is an individual state of the puzzle and each edge is sort of a connection between those two states
其中每个结点是谜题的一个单独的状态，每条边是这两个状态之间的转移
and a state in this case consists of a location of where the boxes are and a connected region where the player is
这种情况下，一个状态是由箱子的位置以及玩家能走的连通区域组成
so individual moves are not considered state changes unless they push a box
因此，玩家单独的移动不会被看做状态变换，除非推动了箱子
um but as you can see with this puzzle there's this really tight bottleneck around down here
但正如你在图中看到的，这下面这里有个非常细的瓶颈
and that's sort of is what makes this puzzle difficult
而这个瓶颈正是使得这个谜题很难的原因
there is one unique sort of key move or trick that you have to do in order to get to the goal
需要有一个独特的关键操作或技巧才能达到目标
（译者注：翻阅原论文可知，点的颜色没有特别意义，点的大小才对应思考时间，
在原论文中这个涂成绿色点的图代表人脑思考的状态图，而论文中有另一个涂成黄色点的图对应计算机随机行走下的状态图）
and the coloring here is based on players trying to attempt to solve this puzzle and how much time they spent in each state of the puzzle
这里的颜色是根据玩家尝试解决这个谜题的情况，以及他们在每个状态下花费的时间
the size of the dot corresponds to how long players spent
点的大小与玩家花费的时间相对应
and you could see that they spend a lot of time not getting through the bottleneck
你可以看到，在通过瓶颈之前他们花了很多时间
and once they get through there's hardly any time spent at all
而一旦他们通过了，就几乎不怎么花时间了
because they're immediately able to get to the goal
因为他们马上就能到达目标了
and so, understanding that state diagram allows you to sort of control aspects of your puzzle by manipulating it
所以，理解并操作状态图可以让你控制谜题的各个方面
the larger the state space is obviously the more difficult the more possible states
显然，状态空间越大，谜题就越困难，可能的状态越多
but the bottlenecks are what create difficulty
但瓶颈是造成困难的原因
and if you have multiple bottlenecks that can make things even more difficult
如果你有多个瓶颈，会使之变得更加困难
this in particular this sokoban puzzle is one that takes an average of 30 to 40 minutes for players to solve
在图中这个推箱子谜题中，玩家平均要花30到40分钟才能解开
this is a really nasty one uh and that bottleneck is the reason
这是个非常棘手的谜题，而那个瓶颈正是原因
could you imagine if this puzzle had a second one afterwards uh players could be here for a long time um
你能想象，如果这个谜题之后还有第二个瓶颈的话，玩家可能会在这里呆很久
so, a related idea is to “understand your puzzle's solution path”
因此，一个相关的一点是「理解你的谜题的解法路径」
and when I say solution path I don't necessarily mean just the path through that state diagram
当我说“解法路径”的时候，我指的不一定是通过状态图的路径
but also the sort of the state of the player as they're solving the puzzle
而是指玩家在解谜过程中的那种状态
and what are all of the understandings or eureka moments that the player will go through
玩家将经历哪些理解或尤里卡时刻
how are they going to make progress through your puzzle
他们将如何在你的谜题中取得进展
（译者注：该讲座的标题为《The Arcane Art of Puzzle Dependency Diagrams》）
Noah Falstein gave a talk in 2013 at GDC
Noah Falstein在2013年的GDC上有一个讲座
where he talked about these dependency diagrams that they used uh for adventure games of the puzzles
他在讲座中谈到了这种他们在冒险解谜游戏中使用的依赖关系图，
and this is sort of like the pre-requisite chain of all the different things you had to do in order to get through this
这就像你为了达到目标所必须做的各种事情的一个先决条件链
this isn't even a whole game this is like the intro sequence to this game
这还不是一个完整游戏的（依赖关系图），这只是一个游戏的序章
and one of the pieces of advice sort of the main piece of advice he gave was to “make these diagrams bushy”
他在讲座中给的主要建议是，让这些图变得“枝繁叶茂”
meaning not a long linear prerequisite chain
意思是说，不用一个长长的先决条件链
but sort of a lot of different things that you could make process on concurrently without them sort of blocking each other as prerequisites
而是应该有很多你可以并行取得进展的不同东西，不要把它们作为先决条件来互相阻隔
and the reason to do this was to
这样做的原因是
allow the player to sort of explore and be able to make progress in multiple areas of the game without restricting them too much
这能使得玩家可以探索以及在多个领域取得进展，而不会对他们造成太多限制
without having that one single bottleneck which would force the player to do this one thing and everywhere else in the game is just kind of useless to them
不会有一个单一的瓶颈，迫使玩家去做这一件事，而游戏中其他地方对他们来说都毫无用处
um Cameron Browne has this interesting illustration where he shows slitherlink puzzles
Cameron Browne有张有趣的图片，他展示了这样一个《数回》（Slitherlink）谜题
and the rules of this puzzle are essentially you're given as input a grid made of dots and some numbers in there
数回的规则是这样的：给你一个由点和数字组成的网格作为输入
and you have to draw a single closed loop uh around this grid
你必须在这个网格上画一个单一的闭环
and the numbers indicate sort of the uh adjacency uh how many edges of that loop are adjacent to the number
而这些数字代表了它相邻着多少条边
so for example this three right here has three walls next to it
比如，这里这个3，旁边有3条边
this one right here has one this this two right here has two
这个1这里有1条边，这个2在这里有两条边
um and slitherlink exists in some video games as well the witness has a version of slitherlink
数回也存在于一些电子游戏中，《见证者》中就有一个数回的版本
there are some other games that have similar ideas
还有其他一些游戏也有类似的想法
um but here on the top he's showing a computer-generated puzzle that was sort of randomly constructed
但在这张图里，上面这个他展示的是一个电脑随机生成的谜题
and on the bottom there's a human-constructed puzzle
下面是一个人工构建的谜题
and the way in which the solver goes from the initial puzzle to the solution is very different for these two puzzles
对于这两个谜题，解谜者从最初的起点到最终解的方式是非常不同的
on the bottom one there's kind of two places you can make progress
在下面这个谜题中，有两个地方你可以作为起点来取得进展
and you sort of linearly do the bottom half the loop and the top half of the loop and they meet together
你可以类似线性地完成下半部分和上半部分的环，然后它们会汇合在一起
whereas this top one you can start just about anywhere on any corner of the grid
而上面这个你可以从网格的任何地方开始
and then you kind of get about this much before you then have to uh solve some more
然后你就只能解出来一点，然后就得（从其他地方开始）进一步解决
here's a bigger example of a human-constructed slitherlink puzzle
这里这个是一个更大的人工构建的数回的例子
where there's sort of like three different places where you can make progress linearly
里面有三个不同的地方，你可以作为起点来线性地取得进展
and then in the middle uh they all come together and make the final solution to the puzzle
然后再中间它们都交汇到一起，称为谜题的最终解
and so, as a solver you can start in a couple of these different corners and make progress
所以作为一个解谜者，你可以从这些不同的角落开始并取得进展
but when you're going along each section there's this sort of smooth flow of
而你在每个部分进行下去的时候，会有一种丝滑的思维流
oh i did this oh now i get this oh now i get this oh now i get this
“噢，我把这个解出来了！我又得到了这个！我又解出了这个！这个也解出来了！”
and it feels very um exciting as a solver to feel that you're on the right track
作为一个解谜者，你会对感觉自己在正确的轨道上感到非常兴奋
and for every bit of progress to then unlock further progress it sort of makes that progress feel even better
而每取得一点进展就能解锁更多进展，这让取得进展的感觉更好
because in addition to solving part of the grid you're also allowing yourself to solve another part of the grid, so it's it's very exciting
因为在解决这部分网格之外，你相当于当自己解决另一部分，因此这是很令人兴奋的
the linear solution path can be much harder especially for a large puzzle
线性的解谜路径可能会难得多，尤其是对于很大的谜题来说
because you may not know where to start if you have a big grid
因为如果你有一个很大的网格的话，你可能不知道从哪里开始
and there's literally only one place where you can make progress then that can take a lot of time to find um
而实际上你又只有一个地方可以开始取得进展，那么就需要花费大量的时间去寻找
whereas if you have a bushy solution path then the solver is less likely to be stuck
而对应的，如果你的解题路径很“枝繁叶茂”、很丰富，那么解谜者就不太可能被卡住
and can sort of proceed from more areas and feel like they're making progress sooner
而且可以从更多的地方取得进展，感觉他们更快地取得了进展
but yeah the linear solution pass can lead to sort of these interesting solution flows
但是，线性的解谜路径能够产生这种有趣的解谜思维流
that can be more of a work of art and can be more exciting um
这会更有艺术性、更令人兴奋
let's see so uh yeah this this is an idea that um we use internally working on our new game
下面这个是我们在开发新游戏时我们团队内部的一个想法
which is how big is the puzzle grid versus how difficult it is
那就是 谜题规模大小 vs 谜题难度
uh you know if it has few steps and it's trivially difficult
如果一个谜题只需要几个步骤，而难度又不大
then it's you know it's whatever it's boring it's a tutorial puzzle it's nothing
那么它就会很无聊，可能是个教程谜题，或者啥也不是
but the two types that are interesting are
但有两种类型会有趣，其中一个是
if you have many steps of low difficulty we call this a flow puzzle
如果谜题有很多步骤，但难度不大，我们称之为“流”型谜题
versus you have few steps but high difficulty maybe only one difficult step
而如果你的步骤不多，但难度很高，也许只有一个困难的步骤
and sort of the whole puzzle is about figuring out that one difficult interesting thing
而整个谜题就是要找出那一个困难的有趣的东西
we call that a gem puzzle
我们称之为“精华”型谜题
and of course if you have many steps in high difficulty then it's just a slog
当然，如果步骤又多难度又大，那它就单纯是艰苦而漫长的谜题
it's going to be you know it's going to take a long time
这将花费很长的时间
it's something you really got to get invested into
需要投入很多时间进去
but the flowy puzzles and the gems are usually the most suitable for video games
但“流”型谜题和“精华”型谜题通常是最适合电子游戏的
and for us they've been the most interesting
对我们来说它们也是最有趣的
um i'm going to take a break and then we will come back for the final part
我要休息一下，稍后我们回来讲最后一部分